<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss xmlns:a10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>News (English) - World Health Organization</title><link>https://www.who.int/</link><description>Corporate news releases, statements, and notes for media issued by the World Health Organization.</description><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:contributor><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:contributor><a10:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://www.who.int/rss-feeds/news-english.xml" /><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:a53e2719-2487-41ad-8ba0-8ffe812f25f7</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/01-05-2020-billions-worldwide-living-with-herpes</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Billions worldwide living with herpes</title><description>&lt;p&gt;About half a billion people worldwide are living with genital herpes, and several billion have an oral herpes infection, new estimates show, highlighting the need to improve awareness and scale up services to prevent and treat herpes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;About 13% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population aged 15 to 49 years were living with herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV-2) infection in 2016, the latest year for which data is available.&amp;nbsp; HSV-2 is almost exclusively sexually transmitted, causing genital herpes. Infection can lead to recurring, often painful, genital sores in up to a third of people infected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) is mainly transmitted by oral to oral contact to cause oral herpes infection &amp;ndash; sometimes leading to painful sores in or around the mouth (&amp;ldquo;cold sores&amp;rdquo;). However, HSV-1 can also be transmitted to the genital area through oral sex, causing genital herpes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 67% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population aged 0 to 49 had HSV-1 infection in 2016 &amp;ndash; an estimated 3.7 billion people. Most of these infections were oral; however, between 122 million to 192 million people were estimated to have genital HSV-1
        infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genital herpes is a substantial health concern worldwide &amp;ndash; beyond the potential pain and discomfort suffered by people living with the infection, the associated social consequences can have a profound effect on sexual and reproductive
        health&amp;rdquo; says Dr Ian Askew, Director of the Department of Sexual and Reproductive Health and Research at the World Health Organization (WHO).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Herpes and HIV&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;People with HSV-2 infection are at least three times more likely to become infected with HIV, if exposed. Thus, HSV-2 likely plays a substantial role in the spread of HIV globally. Women are more susceptible to both HSV-2 and HIV. Women living in
        the WHO Africa Region have the highest HSV-2 prevalence and exposure to HIV &amp;ndash; putting them at greatest risk of HIV infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;No cure: vaccine needed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no cure for herpes. Antiviral medications, such as acyclovir, famciclovir, and valacyclovir, can help to reduce the severity and frequency of symptoms but cannot cure the infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Better awareness, improved access to antiviral medications and heightened HIV prevention efforts for those with genital HSV symptoms are needed globally. In addition, development of better treatment and prevention interventions is needed, particularly
        HSV vaccines.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A vaccine against HSV infection would not only help to promote and protect the health and well-being of millions of people, particularly women, worldwide &amp;ndash; it could also potentially have an impact on slowing the spread of HIV, if developed
        and provided alongside other HIV prevention strategies&amp;rdquo; says Dr Meg Doherty, Director of the WHO Department of Global HIV, Hepatitis, and STI Programmes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Authored by staff at the University of Bristol, the WHO, and Weill Cornell Medical College-Qatar, and published in the Bulletin of the World Health Organization, this new study estimates the global infection prevalence and incidence of HSV-1 and HSV-2
        in 2016.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 07:25:26 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:f242de76-1ca3-4435-990a-cfea3bcaa34c</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/04-05-2020-compendium-of-research-projects-at-the-interface-of-tuberculosis-and-covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Compendium of research projects at the interface of tuberculosis and COVID-19</title><description>&lt;p&gt;As the world comes together to tackle the COVID-19 pandemic, it is important to ensure that Tuberculosis (TB) prevention and care approaches are adapting appropriately to ensure continuous and safe delivery of high-quality TB services. Considering the overlaps in TB and COVID-19 in disease presentation and transmission, the pandemic presents many questions for the TB field that may require learning through research and innovation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To better understand challenges and opportunities in this space, the World Health Organization Global TB Programme is collating information on ongoing research at the interface of TB and COVID-19 (i.e. research which would improve TB prevention and care approaches in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic). We are developing&amp;nbsp;a living compendium (listing), which will be updated&amp;nbsp;periodically to make ongoing research projects and publications visible on its website. With your consent we would like to include any study you have in this compendium.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To fulfill these objectives, we need the cooperation of organizations and individuals engaged in TB/COVID-19 research to complete this&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://who.us8.list-manage.com/track/click?u=f093a7c38a3780cd9504f8d9d&amp;amp;id=e383fc7306&amp;amp;e=09bced52fa"&gt;one page template&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;before&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;20 May 2020&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp;We encourage you to please share this in your network, so we can reach all stakeholders widely.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We&amp;nbsp;thank you in advance for your cooperation, and please do not hesitate to contact us if you have any questions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 15:49:47 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:0d7c66e6-e3e4-48e5-8c08-1d49405503f3</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/01-05-2020-who-and-european-investment-bank-strengthen-efforts-to-combat-covid-19-and-build-resilient-health-systems-to-face-future-pandemics</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO and European Investment Bank strengthen efforts to combat COVID-19 and build resilient health systems to face future pandemics</title><description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;WHO and the European Investment Bank enhance cooperation to support countries in addressing the health impact of COVID-19&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The first phase will address urgent needs and strengthen primary health care in ten African countries&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Enhanced WHO-EIB partnership will scale up financing to assure the chain of essential supplies, including personal protective equipment, diagnostics and clinical management&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;New initiative will accelerate investment in health preparedness and primary health care with a focus on health work force, infrastructure, and water, sanitation and hygiene&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The initiative involves measures to address the growing threat of antimicrobial resistance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The World Health Organization and the European Investment Bank will boost cooperation to strengthen public health, supply of essential equipment, training and hygiene investment in countries most vulnerable to the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new partnership between the United Nations health agency and the world&amp;rsquo;s largest international public bank, announced at WHO headquarters in Geneva earlier today, will help increase resilience to reduce the health and social impact of future health emergencies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Combining the public health experience of the World Health Organization and the financial expertise of the European Investment Bank will contribute to a more effective response to COVID-19 and other pressing health challenges," said Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, WHO Director-General.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"WHO looks forward to strengthening cooperation with the EIB to improve access to essential supplies including medical equipment and training, and deliver better water, sanitation and hygiene where most needed. New initiatives to improve primary health care in Africa and support the EU Malaria Fund hint at the potential impact of our new partnership,&amp;rdquo; Dr Tedros concluded.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The world is facing unprecedented health, social and economic shocks from COVID-19. The European Investment Bank is pleased to join forces with the World Health Organization as a key part of Team Europe&amp;rsquo;s efforts to address the global impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. The EU Bank&amp;rsquo;s new partnership with the WHO will help communities most at risk by scaling up local medical and public health efforts and better protect people around the world from future pandemics. This&amp;nbsp;new cooperation will enable us to combat malaria, address anti-microbial resistance&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;enhance public health in Africa more effectively,&amp;rdquo; said Werner Hoyer, President of the European Investment Bank.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Improving local public health efforts to tackle coronavirus&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The WHO and the EIB will increase cooperation to help governments in low- and middle-income countries to finance and secure access to essential medical supplies and protective equipment through central procurement.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Building resilient health systems in vulnerable countries across Africa&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The WHO and the EIB will reinforce cooperation to support immediate COVID-19 needs and jointly develop targeted financing to enhance health investment and build resilient health systems and primary health care to address public health emergencies as well as accelerate progress towards Universal Health Coverage.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The partnership will benefit from the EIB&amp;rsquo;s planned 1.4 billion EUR response to address the health, social and economic impact of COVID-19 in Africa.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will address immediate needs in the health sector and provide both technical assistance and support for medium-term investment in specialist health infrastructure.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The collaboration envisages rapid identification and fast-track approval of financing for health care, medical equipment and supplies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the collaboration will see public health investment in ten African countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Long-term collaboration to overcome market failures in global health&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement signed today establishes a close collaboration to overcome market failure and stimulate investments in global health, accelerating progress towards Universal Health Coverage. Increased cooperation between the WHO and the EIB will strengthen the resilience of national public health systems and enhance preparedness of vulnerable countries against future pandemics, thanks to investments in primary care infrastructure, health workers and improved water, sanitation and hygiene.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Future cooperation will strengthen the EIB&amp;rsquo;s 5.2 billion EUR global response to COVID-19 outside the European Union.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Scaling up investment to tackle antimicrobial resistance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two organisations will also cooperate in an initiative to address investment barriers hindering development of new antimicrobial treatment and related diagnostics. Antimicrobial resistance is amongst the most significant global health threats.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The WHO and the EIB are working on a new financing initiative to support development of novel antimicrobials and address the estimated 1 billion EUR needed to provide medium-term solutions to antimicrobial resistance. Other crucial partners have been invited to join this discussion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Improving the effectiveness of malaria treatment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the new agreement the EIB and WHO will support development of the EU Malaria Fund, a new 250 million EUR public-private initiative intended to address market failures holding back more effective malaria treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Strengthening EIB support for healthcare, life science and COVID-19 investment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years the European Investment Bank has provided more than 2 billion EUR annually for health care and life science investment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the context of the COVID-19 pandemic, the EIB is currently assessing over 20 projects in the field of vaccine development, diagnostic and treatment, leading to potential investments in the 700 million EUR range. The EIB will also take part in the EU&amp;rsquo;s rolling pledging effort for the coronavirus global response that is taking place on May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;European Investment Bank (EIB)&lt;/strong&gt; is the long-term lending institution of the European Union owned by its Member States. It makes long-term finance available for sound investment in order to contribute towards EU policy goals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/strong&gt; provides global leadership in public health within the United Nations system. Founded in 1948, WHO works with&amp;nbsp;194 Member States, across six regions and from more than 150 offices,&amp;nbsp;to promote health, keep the world safe and serve the vulnerable. Our goal for 2019-2023 is to ensure that a billion more people have universal health coverage, to protect a billion more people from health emergencies, and provide a further billion people with better health and wellbeing. For updates on COVID-19 and public health advice to protect yourself from coronavirus, visit www.who.int and follow WHO on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WHO"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/WHO/"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/who/"&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/world-health-organization/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@who"&gt;TikTok&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.pinterest.ch/worldhealthorganization/"&gt;Pinterest&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.snapchat.com/add/whorg"&gt;Snapchat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.snapchat.com/add/whorg"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/critical-preparedness-readiness-and-response-actions-for-covid-19"&gt;WHO&amp;rsquo;s information site on the COVID-19 pandemic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 13:46:31 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:a20adb7c-a9be-4e3f-827d-1873a53b4d17</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/01-05-2020-statement-on-the-third-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-outbreak-of-coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Statement on the third meeting of the International Health Regulations (2005) Emergency Committee regarding the outbreak of coronavirus disease (COVID-19)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;third&amp;nbsp;meeting of the Emergency Committee convened by the WHO Director-General under the International Health Regulations (2005) (IHR) regarding the coronavirus disease (COVID-19), took place on&amp;nbsp;Thursday, 30&amp;nbsp;April 2020, from 12:00&amp;nbsp;to&amp;nbsp;17:45&amp;nbsp;Geneva
time (CEST). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/ihr/procedures/novel-coronavirus-2019/ec-30042020-members/en/"&gt;Members and advisors of the Emergency Committee&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;were convened by teleconference. Membership of the Emergency Committee was expanded
to reflect the nature of the pandemic and the need to include additional areas of expertise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Director-General welcomed the Committee, thanked them for their commitment to enhancing global public health, and provided an overview of the major achievements in the COVID-19 response since the last Emergency Committee meeting on 30 January 2020.
Representatives of the legal department and the Department of Compliance, Risk Management, and Ethics (CRE) briefed the members on their roles and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ethics Officer from CRE provided the members and advisers with an overview of the WHO Declaration of Interest process. The members and advisers were made aware of their individual responsibility to disclose to WHO, in a timely manner, any interests
of a personal, professional, financial, intellectual or commercial nature that may give rise to a perceived or direct conflict of interest. They were additionally reminded of their duty to maintain the confidentiality of the meeting discussions and
the work of the committee. Only those committee members and advisers who were not considered to have any perceived or direct conflict of interest participated in the meeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat turned the meeting over to the Chair, Professor Houssin.&amp;nbsp;He also welcomed the Committee and reviewed the objectives and agenda of the meeting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WHO Regional Emergency Directors and the Executive Director of the WHO Health Emergencies Programme (WHE) provided regional and the global situation overview. After ensuing discussion, the Committee unanimously agreed that the outbreak still constitutes
a public health emergency of international concern (PHEIC) and offered advice to the Director-General.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Director-General declared that the outbreak of COVID-19 continues to constitute a PHEIC. He accepted the advice of the Committee to WHO and issued the Committee&amp;rsquo;s advice to States Parties as Temporary Recommendations under the IHR.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Emergency Committee will be reconvened within three months or earlier,&amp;nbsp;at the discretion of the Director-General.&amp;nbsp;The Director-General thanked the Committee for its work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advice to WHO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coordination, planning, and monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to lead and coordinate the global response to the COVID-19 pandemic in collaboration with countries, the United Nations (UN), and other partners.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with fragile states and vulnerable countries that require additional technical, logistical and commodity support. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Establish mechanisms to compile lessons learned from country and partner experiences and WHO missions and share the best practices and updated recommendations.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide further guidance to countries about adjusting public health measures, taking into account the different epidemiological situations of the pandemic.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Promote the inclusion of all interested countries, including low- and middle-income countries from all regions, in the Solidarity clinical trials for therapeutics and vaccines. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue efforts with partners to obtain equitable access to personal protective equipment, diagnostics, and biomedical equipment essential to the pandemic COVID-19 response.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to coordinate global expert networks in epidemiology, laboratory, vaccines, clinical care, infection prevention and control, social sciences, and operational research; modelling; and other technical support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One Health &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE), the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), and countries to identify the zoonotic source of the virus and the route of introduction to the human population, including
    the possible role of intermediate hosts. This should be accomplished through efforts such as scientific and collaborative field missions, which will enable targeted interventions and a research agenda to reduce the risk of similar events.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work closely with OIE and FAO to provide guidance on how to prevent &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;SARS-CoV-2 infections in animals and humans and prevent the establishment of new zoonotic reservoirs.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with partner organizations and countries to strengthen the global food supply chain, protect food workers, properly manage food markets, and mitigate possible disruptions to the food supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Essential Health Services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support countries to assess and manage the unintended consequences of public health measures implemented to control the COVID-19 pandemic, including gender-based violence and child neglect. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support countries to monitor their ability to provide and strengthen essential health services throughout a likely extended COVID-19 response. This should include, but is not limited to, essential prevention for communicable diseases, particularly
    vaccination; services related to reproductive health, including care during pregnancy and childbirth; care of vulnerable populations, such as young infants and older adults; provision of medications and supplies for the ongoing management of chronic
    diseases, including mental health conditions; continuity of critical inpatient therapies; management of emergency health conditions and common acute presentations that require time-sensitive intervention; and auxiliary services, such as basic
    diagnostic imaging, laboratory services, and blood bank services.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support countries to address shortages of essential medicines and health products, personal protective equipment, and other medical supplies and to establish sustainable risk management practices to prevent future shortages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Risk communication and community engagement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue risk communications and community engagement activities through the WHO Information Network for Epidemics (EPI-WIN) and other platforms to counter rumours and misinformation. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to regularly communicate clear messages, guidance, and advice about the evolution of the COVID-19 pandemic, how to reduce transmission, and save lives. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with partners and countries to articulate potential long-term consequences of COVID-19 pandemic, emphasizing the need for strengthened cross-sectoral preparedness, transparency and global coordination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Surveillance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Clarify the testing strategy, support countries to increase testing capacity, and aim to provide equitable access to diagnostic tests and supplies in light of market failures and global shortages. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to provide guidance on monitoring disease trends using Severe Acute Respiratory Infections (SARI) and Influenza Like Illness (ILI) surveillance systems in anticipation of the co-circulation of influenza viruses.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Develop qualitative and quantitative indicators that countries can use to assess and monitor SARS-CoV-2 transmission at all levels of public health response.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to support countries and partners by providing technical and operational guidance, training platforms, and tools such as Go.Data,to enhance case identification and contact tracing capacity, strengthen the public health workforce, and engage
    communities for contact tracing.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide clear qualitative and quantitative indicators to monitor SARS-CoV-2 transmission to inform the adjustment of public health and social measures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Travel and Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue working with countries and partners to enable essential travel needed for pandemic response, humanitarian relief, repatriation, and cargo operations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Develop strategic guidance with partners for the gradual return to normal operations of passenger travel in a coordinated manner that provides appropriate protection when physical distancing is not feasible. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Update recommendations on appropriate travel measures and analyze their effects on international transmission of COVID-19, with consideration of the balance between benefits and unintended consequences, including entry and exit screening, education
    of travelers on responsible travel behaviour, case finding, contact tracing, isolation, and quarantine, by incorporating evidence on the potential role of pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic transmission. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To all States Parties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coordination and Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support WHO leadership and continue to collaborate with WHO at all levels of the organization and with other countries to enable effective global COVID-19 pandemic preparedness and response. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Participate in global solidarity efforts to enable access to essential supplies for all.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Document and share lessons learned from efforts to control the pandemic, including the timing, pace, and sequencing of the application and lifting of public health measures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparedness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Strengthen&amp;nbsp;preparedness&amp;nbsp;for health emergencies, and build resilient health systems, incorporating lessons learned during different stages of the pandemic, and sharing experiences&amp;nbsp;with other countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Surveillance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with WHO and multisectoral partners to interrupt transmission by maintaining robust surveillance systems; enhancing capacities for case detection, testing, isolation of cases, contact tracing, quarantine of contacts, and rapid response; strengthening
    the public health workforce; and actively engaging communities for contact tracing, with a particular focus on high risk areas. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In settings where testing a large proportion of suspected cases is not possible, monitor overall trends; undertake early detection through laboratory confirmation of a limited number of cases with a focus on health workers; and rapidly implement
    public health measures.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Share with WHO all data necessary to conduct global risk assessments through data platforms, such as the Global Influenza Surveillance and Response System and the IHR mechanism. These data should include SARI and ILI where available.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Use the WHO qualitative and quantitative indicators to assess and monitor SARS-CoV-2 transmission at all levels of public health response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Health Measures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Avoid restrictions on international transport of food, medical and other essential supplies and permit the safe movement of essential personnel required for an effective pandemic response. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Implement appropriate travel measures with consideration of their public health benefits, including entry and exit screening, education of travelers on responsible travel behaviour, case finding, contact tracing, isolation, and quarantine, by
    incorporating evidence on the potential role of pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic transmission. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Implement and monitor case finding and contact tracing of travellers, using digital tools where appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to review travel and trade measures based on regular risk assessments, transmission patterns at origin and destination, cost-benefit analysis, evolution of the pandemic, and new knowledge of COVID-19. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Engage in global efforts to respond to the challenges of COVID-19 in managing maritime vessels. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do not implement trade restrictions beyond those considered to be of public health importance in accordance with relevant international agreements.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to provide appropriate public health rationale to WHO for additional health measures in accordance with IHR. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health Workers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Prioritize the protection of the health workforce through access to training and provision of personal protective equipment, infection prevention and control measures, improved working conditions, application of WHO recommended testing strategies,
    and prevention of stigma and attacks on health workers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Food Security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work with WHO and partners to strengthen the global food supply chain, protect food workers, properly manage food markets, and mitigate possible disruptions to the food supply, especially for vulnerable populations. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Promote sound practices to manage risks of trade of live animals in food markets and regulate trade of exotic wildlife. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Risk Communications and Community Engagement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to engage communities to address rumours and misinformation and keep the public informed, with a focus on vulnerable populations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research and development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Address research gaps such as: routes of transmission, including the role of asymptomatic and pre-symptomatic infection droplet, contact, fomite and aerosol transmission; and viral shedding; and animal source and intermediate hosts, in collaboration
    with partners. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to support and conduct COVID-19 research, in line with the WHO Research and Development Blueprint, and the road map for COVID-19 vaccines, diagnostics, and therapeutics.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue sharing full genome sequences to increase global understanding of virus evolution and phylogenetics and their application to public health practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Essential Health Services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Maintain essential health services throughout a likely extended COVID-19 response. This should include essential prevention for communicable diseases, particularly vaccination; services related to reproductive health, including care during pregnancy
    and childbirth; care of vulnerable populations, such as young infants and older adults; provision of medications and supplies for the ongoing management of chronic diseases, including mental health conditions; continuity of critical inpatient
    therapies; management of emergency health conditions and common acute presentations that require time-sensitive intervention; and auxiliary services, such as basic diagnostic imaging, laboratory services, and blood bank services.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Continue to track and document the impact of COVID-19 on essential health services. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 15:45:55 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:182f05e8-0115-4e27-a7b7-dcada4ca05cc</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/01-05-2020-massive-proportion-world-population-living-with-herpes-infection</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Massive proportion of world’s population are living with herpes infection</title><description>&lt;h2&gt;Virus causing genital herpes may put millions of people at greater risk of infection with HIV&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About half a billion people worldwide are living with genital herpes, and several billion have an oral herpes infection, new estimates show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authored by staff at the University of Bristol, World Health Organization (WHO), and Weill Cornell Medical College-Qatar, and published in the &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/bulletin"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/bulletin/volumes/98/5/19-237149.pdf"&gt;Bulletin of the World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt;,
the new study estimates the global infection prevalence and incidence of herpes simplex virus types 1 and 2 (HSV-1 and HSV-2) in 2016.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Herpes infection affects millions of people across the globe and can have far-reaching health effects. We need more investment and commitment to develop better treatment and prevention tools for this infection.&amp;rdquo; says Dr Sami Gottlieb, Medical
Officer at WHO and an author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prevalence and incidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An estimated 491.5 million people were living with HSV-2 infection in 2016, equivalent to 13.2% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population aged 15 to 49 years. HSV-2 is almost exclusively sexually transmitted, causing infection in the genital or anal area (genital
herpes).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An estimated 3.7 billion people had HSV-1 infection during the same year &amp;ndash; around 66.6% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population aged 0 to 49. HSV-1 is mainly transmitted by oral to oral contact to cause infection in or around the mouth (oral herpes). However,
HSV-1 can also be transmitted to the genital area through oral-genital contact &amp;ndash; during oral sex &amp;ndash; to cause genital herpes. Most HSV-1 infections were oral; however, between 122 million to 192 million people were estimated to have genital
HSV-1 infection, depending on the assumptions used in the estimation model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because herpes is a lifelong infection, estimated prevalence increased with age; HSV-2 prevalence was also higher among women and in the WHO African Region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health and social impacts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people living with herpes, caused by either HSV-1 or 2, are unaware they have the infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When symptoms do occur however, oral herpes infection can lead to painful sores around the mouth (&amp;ldquo;cold sores&amp;rdquo;). Genital herpes infection can cause recurring, often painful, genital sores, often referred to as genital ulcer disease.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHO and partners published &lt;a href="https://gh.bmj.com/content/5/3/e001875"&gt;a study in March 2020&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;estimating that around 5% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population (187 million people) suffered from at least one episode of herpes-related genital ulcer disease in 2016 (1). Most of these episodes were due to
HSV-2, which can recur frequently over many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recurrent symptoms of genital herpes can lead to stigma and psychological distress, and can have an important impact on quality of life and sexual relationships. However, in time, most people with herpes adjust to living with the infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Genital herpes is a substantial health concern worldwide &amp;ndash; beyond the potential pain and discomfort suffered by people living with the infection, the associated social consequences can have a profound effect on sexual and reproductive health&amp;rdquo;
says Dr Ian Askew, Director of the Department of Sexual and Reproductive Health and Research at WHO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Herpes and HIV&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong association exists between HSV-2 infection and HIV infection. In 2019, WHO commissioned a &lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/laninf/article/PIIS1473-3099(19)30470-0/fulltext"&gt;modeling study&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to estimate how much HSV-2 infection might contribute to HIV incidence. The study estimated that almost 30% of new sexually acquired HIV
infections in 2016 worldwide were likely attributable to HSV-2 infection (2).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence shows that people with HSV-2 infection are at least three times more likely to become infected with HIV, if exposed. HSV-2 leads to inflammation and small breaks in the genital and anal skin that can make it easier for HIV to cause infection.
In addition, people with both HIV and HSV-2 infection are more likely to spread HIV to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women have higher biologic susceptibility to both HSV-2 and HIV. Women living in the WHO Africa Region have the highest HSV-2 prevalence and exposure to HIV &amp;ndash; putting them at greatest risk of HIV infection, with negative implications for their health
and well-being.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For people living with HIV (or who are living with other conditions that compromise their immune systems) as well as HSV-2, the symptoms of herpes can be more severe and more frequent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Neonatal herpes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neonatal herpes can occur when an infant is exposed to HSV in the genital tract during delivery. This is a rare condition, occurring in an estimated 10 out of every 100,000 births globally, but can lead to lasting neurologic disability or death. The risk
for neonatal herpes is greatest when a mother acquires HSV infection for the first time in late pregnancy. Women who have genital herpes before they become pregnant are at very low risk of transmitting HSV to their infants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No cure &amp;ndash; better treatment and prevention needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no cure for herpes. At present, antiviral medications, such as acyclovir, famciclovir, and valacyclovir, can help to reduce the severity and frequency of symptoms but cannot cure the infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as increasing awareness about HSV infection and its symptoms, improved access to antiviral medications and heightened HIV prevention efforts for those with genital HSV symptoms are needed globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, development of better treatment and prevention interventions is needed, particularly HSV vaccines. WHO and partners are working to accelerate research to develop new strategies for prevention and control of HSV infections. Such research includes
the development of HSV vaccines and topical microbicides. Several candidate vaccines and microbicides are currently being studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A vaccine against HSV infection would not only help to promote and protect the health and well-being of millions of people, particularly women, worldwide &amp;ndash; it could also potentially have an impact on slowing the spread of HIV, if developed
and provided alongside other HIV prevention strategies&amp;rdquo; says Dr Meg Doherty, Director of the WHO&amp;nbsp;Department of&amp;nbsp;Global&amp;nbsp;HIV, Hepatitis,&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;STI&amp;nbsp;Programmes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Related publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/250693/9789241549875-eng.pdf"&gt;WHO guidelines for the treatment of&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Genital Herpes Simplex Virus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/312344/9789241515580-eng.pdf"&gt;WHO preferred product characteristics for herpes simplex virus vaccines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;----------------------&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) &lt;a href="https://gh.bmj.com/content/5/3/e001875"&gt;Looker KJ, Johnston C, Welton NJ, et al. The global and regional burden of genital ulcer disease due to herpes simplex virus: a natural history modelling study. BMJ Glob Health. 2020;5(3):e001875. doi: 10.1136/bmjgh-2019- 001875&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) &lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/laninf/article/PIIS1473-3099(19)30470-0/fulltext"&gt;Looker KJ, Welton NJ, Sabin KM, et al.Global and regional estimates of the contribution of herpes simplex virus type 2 infection to HIV incidence: a population attributable fraction analysis using published epidemiological data. Lancet Infect Dis.2020;20(2):240-249. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30470-0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 22:17:09 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:88adbd7b-e699-45c4-b28d-2082ff827c5d</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/29-04-2020-indonesia-firmly-committed-to-eliminating-lymphatic-filariasis-as-a-public-health-problem</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Indonesia firmly committed to eliminating lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem</title><description>Indonesia recently completed the last of its annual large-scale treatment for lymphatic filariasis (also known as elephantiasis or Penyakit Kaki Gajah) in Malaka District located in its southernmost province, East Nusa Tenggara. Unprecedented progress by the National Lymphatic Filariasis Elimination Programme has strongly placed the country on the path to achieving the elimination of lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem.</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 09:38:09 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;Indonesia recently completed the last of its annual large-scale treatment for lymphatic filariasis (also known as elephantiasis or&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Penyakit Kaki Gajah&lt;/em&gt;) in Malaka District located in its southernmost province, East Nusa Tenggara. Unprecedented
    progress by the National Lymphatic Filariasis Elimination Programme has strongly placed the country on the path to achieving the elimination of lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;&amp;ldquo;We reached an estimated number of 40.7 million people living in the 118 high-risk districts during this month-long treatment campaign in October 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;&amp;rdquo; said Dr Anung Sugihantono, who recently retired as Director General of Diseases
    Prevention and Control, Ministry of Health Indonesia. &amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;Single doses of diethylcarbamazine citrate and albendazole facilitated by WHO were delivered to all eligible populations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2010, an estimated 125 million Indonesians were still at risk of the disease and required treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But things changed considerably in 2015 when Indonesia mounted an annual national campaign to resolutely address transmission of the disease and to tackle the morbidity and disability associated with it. The results were apparent as early as 2017, with
    remarkable progress.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, LF is considered a significant public health concern. In 2009, risk mapping identified a population of 124.5 million people needing treatment for LF. The country initiated a national level LF elimination campaign in 2015, addressing both
    disease prevention and management.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;In 2017 and in just two years we managed to achieve 100% geographical coverage of all people requiring treatment&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; said Dr Sugihantono.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It meant achieving more than 78% epidemiological coverage &amp;ndash; much higher than the generally recommended 65% to stop transmission.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transmission of lymphatic filariasis can be stopped through large-scale treatment (or mass drug administration - MDA) of entire at- risk communities with recommended medicines once a year. These medicines kill the microfilariae in an infected patient's
    blood preventing mosquitoes to transmit&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;the disease to others. Through mass treatment, the aim is to reduce the reservoir of microfilariae in the blood to a level insufficient to maintain transmission by the mosquito vector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy to interrupt transmission is the corner-stone of the World Health Organization&amp;rsquo;s (WHO) Global Program to Eliminate Lymphatic Filariasis (GPELF). Indonesia has been using the GPELF&amp;rsquo;s strategy since 2002 using a district or city
    as its implementation unit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2005, it listed the elimination of LF as a national priority for controlling infectious diseases and the medicines it has been using in large-scale treatment programmes are diethylcarbamazine citrate (DEC) and albendazole&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;which are
    largely distributed by volunteer community health workers&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Community health volunteers are themselves members of the community and know how to reach people effectively to improve compliance&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; said Dr. Stefanus Bria Seran, the Regent of Malaka District, one of LF endemic district in Indonesia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Besides ensuring every single person ingests the medicine given to them, these community workers help in disseminating information well before a large-scale treatment campaign and also assist in reporting activities related to each treatment campaign&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indonesia&amp;rsquo;s efforts to eliminate lymphatic filariasis began in the 1970s but faced numerous challenges including programme coordination in the many inhabited islands, conducting information, education and awareness programmes, lack of capacity and
    insufficient medicines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the situation in Indonesia is unusual than in many other countries endemic for lymphatic filariasis as the country is endemic for all three species of thread-like filarial worms -&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;Brugia malayi, Brugia timori&lt;/em&gt;, and&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Wuchereria bancrofti&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash;
 that cause the disease. Most of the infections in Indonesia, however, are caused by&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;B. malayi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past, some of the factors that prevented access to the medicines (DEC and albendazole) were social stigmatization linked to the disease, the vast geography of the territory and challenges in reaching remote populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With an estimated population of 242 million, Indonesia is the world's largest island nation and consists of approximately 17,000 islands, of which 5,000&amp;ndash;6,000 are inhabited. It is the fourth most populated nation behind China, India, and the United
    States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indonesia is endemic for many other neglected tropical diseases and an estimated 110 million Indonesians are believed to suffer from at least one neglected tropical disease (NTD), including lymphatic filariasis and soil-transmitted helminth infections.
    Leptospirosis (not classified as NTD) is also widespread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indonesia is the only country of WHO&amp;rsquo;s South East Asia Region with endemic schistosomiasis. Like many other countries of the Region, it also faces recurrent threats of dengue outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Global progress&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The world has made significant progress towards the elimination of lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sixteen countries&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;and one territory are now acknowledged by WHO to have achieved elimination of lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seven additional countries have successfully implemented recommended strategies, stopped large-scale treatment and are under surveillance to demonstrate that elimination has been achieved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The disease&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lymphatic filariasis is caused by infection with parasitic worms living in the lymphatic system. The larval stages of the parasite (microfilaria) circulate in the blood and are transmitted from person to person by mosquitoes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infection involves asymptomatic, acute, and chronic conditions. Most infections are asymptomatic, showing no external signs while contributing to transmission of the parasite. Although asymptomatic, these infections still cause damage to the lymphatic
    system and the kidneys and alter the body's immune system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When lymphatic filariasis develops into chronic conditions it leads to lymphoedema (tissue swelling) or elephantiasis (skin/tissue thickening) of limbs and hydrocele (scrotal swelling). Involvement of breasts and genital organs are common.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manifestation of the disease after infection takes time and can result in an altered lymphatic system, causing abnormal enlargement of body parts, and leading to severe disability and social stigmatization of those affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;Lymphatic filariasis is transmitted by different types of mosquitoes &amp;ndash; e.g the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Culex&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;mosquito which widespread across urban and semi-urban areas; Anopheles, mainly found in rural areas; and,&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Aedes&lt;/em&gt;, mainly
    in endemic islands in the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;In 2017, WHO recommended an alternative three drug treatment to accelerate the global elimination of lymphatic filariasis. The treatment, known as IDA, involves a combination of&amp;nbsp;ivermectin,&amp;nbsp;diethylcarbamazine citrate and&amp;nbsp;albendazole.
    It is recommended annually in settings where its use is expected to have the greatest impact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;Community health workers, also called &amp;lsquo;cadres&amp;rsquo;, are volunteers who form part of the communities they serve and work with local
communities to educate families. Their contribution in promoting health has been significant in the country.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;Cambodia, The Cook Islands, Egypt, Kiribati, Maldives, Marshall Islands, Niue, Palau, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Togo, Tonga, Vanuatu, Viet Nam, Wallis and Futuna, and Yemen&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:60a2cccd-9614-4be7-a98e-ea6eebee227e</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/29-04-2020-new-estimates-highlight-need-to-step-up-the-response-to-hepatitis-d</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>New estimates highlight need to step up the response to hepatitis D</title><description>In a study published in the Journal of Hepatology,  Professor Anna Maria Geretti and Dr Alexander Stockdale from the University of Liverpool (United Kingdom), in collaboration with researchers from WHO and the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), estimate that worldwide, hepatitis D virus (HDV) affects nearly 5% of people who have a chronic infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV), and that HDV co-infection could explain about 1 in 5 cases of liver disease and liver cancer in people with HBV infection.</description><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 07:17:18 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lyon, France, 29 April 2020&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; In a study published in the Journal of Hepatology,&lt;sup&gt; 1&lt;/sup&gt; Professor Anna Maria Geretti and Dr Alexander Stockdale from the University of Liverpool (United Kingdom), in collaboration with researchers
    from the World Health Organization (WHO) and the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), estimate that worldwide, hepatitis D virus (HDV) affects nearly 5% of people who have a chronic infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and that HDV
    co-infection could explain about 1 in 5 cases of liver disease and liver cancer in people with HBV infection..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To map the epidemiology of HDV infection in the world, Professor Geretti and Dr Stockdale joined forces with the WHO Global Hepatitis Programme and IARC, alongside investigators in Germany, Malawi, and the United Kingdom. &amp;ldquo;Infection with HDV occurs
    in about 1 in 22 cases of chronic HBV infection in the world,&amp;rdquo; Dr Stockdale says. &amp;ldquo;More high-quality data are needed, but we have identified several geographical hotspots of high prevalence of HDV infection: in Mongolia, the Republic of
    Moldova, and countries in Western and Middle Africa.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Although it is less common than hepatitis B, hepatitis D is a serious disease that often affects underprivileged and vulnerable populations,&amp;rdquo; says Dr Meg Doherty, Director of the WHO Global Hepatitis Programme. Those who are more likely to
    have HBV and HDV co-infection include people who inject drugs and people with hepatitis C virus or HIV infection. The risk of co-infection also appears to be higher in recipients of haemodialysis, men who have sex with men, and commercial sex workers.
    Dr Doherty points out, &amp;ldquo;This information helps in identifying the groups with HBV among whom we should be looking for HDV.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HDV (formerly known as the Delta agent) is a small virus &amp;ndash; one of the smallest that is known to cause disease in humans &amp;ndash; and can replicate only in the presence of HBV, from which HDV borrows some of its structures. Compared with people with
    HBV infection alone, those who have a chronic infection with both HBV and HDV have a much higher risk of developing disease in the form of cirrhosis and liver cancer. &amp;ldquo;HDV is a significant contributor to severe liver disease and liver cancer,&amp;rdquo;
    says IARC scientist Dr Catherine de Martel. &amp;ldquo;The findings from this study inform our work on the association between viral infections and cancer, which is focused on developing improved prevention strategies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Geretti concludes, &amp;ldquo;HDV has long been neglected, because for decades the prevalence of infection remained uncertain and effective treatment was lacking. Mapping the epidemiology of the infection is just the first step. More efforts are
    needed to reduce the global burden of chronic hepatitis B and develop medicines that are safe and effective against hepatitis D and are affordable enough to be deployed on a large scale to those who are most in need.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Stockdale AJ, Kreuels B, Henrion MYR, Giorgi E, Kyomuhangi I, de Martel C, Hutin Y, Geretti AM (2020). The global prevalence of hepatitis D virus infection: systematic review and meta-analysis. J Hepatol. Published online 23 April 2020;
    &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2020.04.008" target="_blank"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2020.04.008&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;For more information, please contact&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;V&amp;eacute;ronique Terrasse, Communications Group, at +33 (0)6 45 28 49 52 or &lt;a href="http://mailto:terrassev@iarc.fr"&gt;terrassev@iarc.fr&lt;/a&gt; or IARC Communications, at &lt;a href="http://mailto:com@iarc.fr"&gt;com@iarc.fr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) is part of the World Health Organization. Its mission is to coordinate and conduct research on the causes of human cancer, the mechanisms of carcinogenesis, and to develop scientific strategies for
    cancer control. The Agency is involved in both epidemiological and laboratory research and disseminates scientific information through publications, meetings, courses, and fellowships. If you wish your name to be removed from our press release emailing
    list, please write to &lt;a href="http://mailto:com@iarc.fr"&gt;com@iarc.fr&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About University of Liverpool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1881 as the original &amp;lsquo;red brick&amp;rsquo;, the University of Liverpool is one of the UK&amp;rsquo;s leading research-intensive higher education institutions. Consistently ranked in the top 200 universities worldwide, we are a member of the prestigious
    Russell Group and have a global reach and influence that reflects our academic heritage as one of the country&amp;rsquo;s largest civic institutions. For more information please visit us at &lt;a href="https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/" target="_blank"&gt;www.liverpool.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:a652cde5-f156-4391-80c0-fb1a419eea94</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-04-2020-new-faqs-address-healthcare-workers-questions-on-breastfeeding-and-covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>New FAQs address healthcare workers questions on breastfeeding and COVID-19</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Mothers and healthcare workers who support them have many questions and concerns about whether it is safe for mothers with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 to be close to and breastfeed their babies during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To address their questions, WHO has released a list of &lt;em&gt;Frequently asked questions: Breastfeeding and COVID-19&lt;/em&gt;. The FAQ complements the WHO interim guidance: &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/clinical-management-of-severe-acute-respiratory-infection-when-novel-coronavirus-(ncov)-infection-is-suspected"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clinical management of severe acute respiratory infection when COVID-19 is suspected&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and draws upon other WHO recommendations on infant and young child feeding&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FAQs aim to provide information to healthcare workers supporting mothers and families in maternity services and community settings, and communicate how the interim guidance should be implemented. Additionally, the FAQs provide information about the protective effects of breastfeeding and skin-to-skin contact, and the harmful effects of inappropriate use of infant formula milk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accompanying the FAQs is a decision tree which provides step-by-step guidance to health workers on how to support mothers with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 to breastfeed. It provides advice on what to do if mothers are not well enough to breastfeed, as well as appropriate hygiene measures for mothers, including wearing a medical mask if available, to reduce the possibility of the COVID-19 virus being spread to her infant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits of breastfeeding outweigh potential risks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 virus has not been detected in the breastmilk of any mother with confirmed and suspected COVID-19 and there is no evidence so far that the virus is transmitted through breastfeeding. Researchers continue to test breastmilk from mothers with the infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO recommends that all mothers with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 continue to have skin-to-skin contact and to breastfeed. In all socio-economic settings, breastfeeding improves survival and provides lifelong health and development advantages to newborns and infants. Breastfeeding also reduces the risk of breast and ovarian cancer for the mother. Skin-to-skin contact, including kangaroo mother care, reduces neonatal mortality, especially for low birth weight newborns.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While infants and children can contract COVID-19, they are at low risk of infection. The few confirmed cases of COVID-19 in young children to date have experienced only mild or asymptomatic illness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO&amp;rsquo;s recommendations on the care and feeding of infants whose mothers have confirmed or suspected COVID-19 aim to improve the immediate and lifelong survival, health and development of their newborns and infants. These recommendations consider the likelihood and potential risks of COVID-19 in infants and also the risks of serious illness and death when infants are not breastfed or when infant formula milk are used inappropriately.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/q-a-on-covid-19-and-breastfeeding"&gt;WHO&amp;rsquo;s Q&amp;amp;A on breastfeeding and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; also provides additional infection prevention advice to mothers with confirmed or suspected COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 12:55:36 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:59b3a9e1-5205-4375-9b6b-541682b73016</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-04-2020-GDO-country-profiles</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>New GDO country profiles available</title><description>Countries across the six WHO regions are participating in the Global Dementia Observatory (GDO), a data and knowledge exchange platform. The GDO provides easy access to country-level key dementia data and functions as the monitoring mechanism of the Global dementia action plan on the public health response to dementia 2017-2025.</description><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 12:29:48 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Countries across the six WHO regions are participating in the Global Dementia Observatory (GDO), a data and knowledge exchange platform. The GDO provides easy access to country-level key dementia data and functions as the monitoring mechanism of the &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/mental_health/neurology/dementia/action_plan_2017_2025/en/"&gt;Global dementia action plan on the public health response to dementia 2017-2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GDO country profiles offer a baseline summary of countries&amp;rsquo; progress on dementia actions outlined in the global dementia action plan. They provide an easy read snapshot of the more comprehensive data submitted by Member States across three key domains related to dementia: policies, service delivery, and information and research. GDO country profiles can be used to inform policy, service planning and health and social care systems decisions for dementia. Additional country profiles will be added as data becomes available. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/mental_health/neurology/dementia/GDO_country_profiles/en/"&gt;View GDO country profiles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/mental_health/neurology/dementia/Global_Observatory/en/"&gt;Access the GDO&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/mental_health/neurology/dementia/gdo_reference_guide/en/"&gt;Read the GDO Reference Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:f9824d16-1d1c-4dce-b0cd-7539ca44482f</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-04-2020-who-calls-for-healthy-safe-and-decent-working-conditions-for-all-health-workers-amidst-covid-19-pandemic</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO calls for healthy, safe and decent working conditions for all health workers, amidst COVID-19 pandemic</title><description>28 April 2020 - On World Day for Safety and Health at Work, the World Health Organization calls upon all governments, employers and workers organizations and the global community to take urgent measures for strengthen countries’ capacities to protect occupational health and safety of health workers and emergency responders respect their rights to decent working conditions, and develop national programmes for occupational health of health workers and to provide them with occupational health services. Amidst the COVID-19 pandemic, ILO has dedicated World Day for Safety and Health at Work 2020 in addressing the outbreak of infectious diseases at work, in particular, on the COVID-19 pandemic.</description><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:02:01 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="color:#4B4B4B;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;On World Day for Safety and Health at Work, the World Health Organization calls upon all governments, employers and workers organizations and the global community to take urgent measures for strengthen countries&amp;rsquo; capacities to protect occupational health and safety of health workers and emergency responders respect their rights to decent working conditions, and develop national programmes for occupational health of health workers and to provide them with occupational health services. Amidst the COVID-19 pandemic, ILO has dedicated World Day for Safety and Health at Work 2020 in addressing the outbreak of infectious diseases at work, in particular, on the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health workers are at the front line of the COVID-19 outbreak response and as such are exposed to hazards that put them at risk of infection. Hazards include pathogen exposure, long working hours, psychological distress, fatigue, occupational burnout, stigma, and physical and psychological violence. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infections with COVID-19, insufficient measures for infection prevention and control, occupational safety and health, mental health and psychosocial support for health workers result in high rates of absenteeism and deplete the health workforce &amp;ndash; the most precision resources for stopping the COVID outbreak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Messages and Facts &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;COVID-19 infections among health workers:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As of 21 April 2020 countries reported to WHO that over 35, 000 health workers were infected with COVID19. This number is significantly higher because of underreporting.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The major occupational risks for COVID19 infection among health workers are:&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;late recognition or suspicion of COVID-19 in patients, working in a higher-risk department, longer duty hours, sub-optimal adherence to infection prevention and control measures, such as hand hygiene practices, and lack of or improper use of personal protective equipment (PPE). Other factors have also been documented, such as inadequate or insufficient IPC training for respiratory pathogens, including the COVID-19 virus, as well as long exposure in areas in healthcare facilities where large numbers of COVID-19 patients were being cared for.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The prevention of infections requires the use of appropriate infection prevention and control measures by all health workers, with a special focus on the adherence to hand hygiene and personal protective equipment when caring for COVID-19 patients, as well as a combination of environmental and administrative controls &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Health workers infected with COVID-19 following exposure in the workplace should have the right to employment injury benefits for occupational disease, including compensation, rehabilitation, and curative services.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Violence and stigma against health workers: &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Health workers are at high risk of violence all over the world. Between 8% and 38% of health workers suffer physical violence at some point in their careers. Many more are threatened or exposed to verbal aggression and social stigma because of their work. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In the COVID19 crisis, shortage of staff and resources and increasing social tensions result in increased level of violence against health workers and even attacks against health care facilities. Doctors, nurses, security personnel and those who are assisting in testing, tracing contacts and enforcing physical distancing measures to stop COVID-19 experience threats and aggression.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;WHO calls upon governments, employers and workers organizations to institute measures for zero-tolerance to violence against health workers at the workplace and at the way to and from their workplace, and for intensifying social support and respect for health workers and their families. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Long working hours and psychosocial hazards for health workers: &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many health workers have to work longer or irregular hours because of the increasing demand for health services. In addition, many countries experience shortage of health workers, or junior staff are working in demanding new roles. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Health workers face psychosocial hazards, which are exacerbated during emergencies where demands increase and they have to experience risk of infection witness higher suffering or mortality. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Long working hours, shift work, high workload and other psychosocial hazards can lead to fatigue, occupational burnout, increased psychological distress or declining mental health - affecting the health of health workers, and the quality and safety of care delivered.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;WHO calls for adequate staffing levels and clinical rotation in healthcare facilities, measures to minimize psychosocial hazards, and provision of access to mental health and psychosocial support for health workers. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The annual World Day for Safety and Health at Work on 28 April promotes the prevention of occupational accidents and diseases globally. It is an awareness-raising campaign intended to focus international attention on the magnitude of the problem and on how promoting and creating a safety and health culture can help reduce the number of work-related deaths and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:0adf8d3f-994c-4a1f-a5ab-af5ec9771ffd</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/27-04-2020-maternal-infections-in-health-facilities</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Maternal infections in health facilities</title><description>&lt;h2&gt;A clearer picture of the global impact&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New research from the&lt;strong&gt; Global Maternal Sepsis Study&lt;/strong&gt; (GLOSS), a major WHO/HRP initiative, shows that infection has a much larger impact on global maternal mortality and morbidity than previously thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30109-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X(20)30109-1/fulltext"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X(20)30109-1/fulltext"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.who.int/images/default-source/departments/reproductive-health/logos/lancet-global.jpg?sfvrsn=78fd2c64_4" style="float:right;margin:5px 0px 5px 5px;" title="lancet-global" data-displaymode="Original" alt="Logo of the Lancet Global Health" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The
results from GLOSS, &lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X(20)30109-1/fulltext"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;published in &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Global Health&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, are the first to provide data on frequency of maternal infections and
sepsis across the pregnancy and post-pregnancy period, in a large number of health facilities around the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 11 women per 1000 live births had an infection which resulted in or contributed to what is known as a severe maternal outcome &amp;ndash; either they died or nearly died &amp;ndash; during their hospitalization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urgent improvement is needed to manage this life-threatening risk faced by all pregnant and recently pregnant women, wherever they are in the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is maternal sepsis and how does it lead to maternal death?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maternal sepsis is a life-threatening condition that arises when the body&amp;rsquo;s response to infection causes injury to its own tissues and organs during pregnancy, child-birth, post-abortion or the postpartum period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest global estimates place sepsis due to obstetric infections as the third most common cause of maternal mortality. However, this only includes infections as a direct result of pregnancy, such as endometritis or post-caesarean wound infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few
previous studies include post-abortion infections. Neither do they address indirect infections such as respiratory and meningitis, which are aggravated by pregnancy but not directly caused by it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A better understanding of maternal infection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS was a massive facility-based data collection effort led by WHO, accompanied by a &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://srhr.org/sepsis/"&gt;STOP SEPSIS!&amp;rsquo; campaign&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to increase awareness among healthcare providers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study gathered data on women who were admitted with suspected or confirmed infection during pregnancy or post-pregnancy over a one-week period in 2017. More than 2800 women participated in the study in 52 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS included healthcare facilities that care for women during pregnancy, childbirth or at the end of pregnancy, as well as facilities without maternity service but where women could be hospitalized during or after pregnancy, and data on infections
which are not usually recorded as maternal sepsis, including post-abortion and indirect infections.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a more complete understanding of the frequency and impact of maternal infections in health facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS calls attention not only to the wider range of risks faced by pregnant women but also to the long period of time during which they are at risk.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting global numbers on maternal infection and sepsis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, around 70 pregnant or recently-pregnant women per 1000 live births were found to have a maternal infection needing hospital management.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the study, 11 women with either direct or indirect infection per 1000 live births developed a severe maternal outcome, but in low- and middle-income countries up to 15 women per 1000 births were affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infections were the underlying cause of most of the deaths recorded during the study, primarily post-abortion infection and indirect infections. Infections were also present in about a third of deaths attributed to other causes, such as postpartum
haemorrhage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests that the contribution of infection to global maternal mortality and morbidity may be larger than current reports of maternal sepsis mortality suggest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preventing, identifying and treating maternal infection and sepsis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most common maternal infections found in the study, such as urinary tract infections, post-caesarean and post-abortion infections, are largely preventable and treatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS results suggest that current levels of monitoring and clinical care across health facilities are not enough to prevent, identify and treat levels of maternal infection effectively.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a complete set of vital signs was not reported for a third of the women in the study, on the day their infection was suspected or diagnosed. Delays in antimicrobial therapy were frequent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS also shows marked differences across countries, with the highest burden in low- and middle-income countries, compared with high-income countries.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may reflect the impact of broader health determinants in different country contexts. Challenges of overcrowding, limited access to water and sanitation and constraints to safe births by skilled birth attendants can reduce the ability of healthcare
providers to manage the frequency and outcome of maternal infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An opportunity to implement evidence-based practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLOSS gives healthcare providers, policy-makers, and the public at large an opportunity: to &lt;a href="https://srhr.org/sepsis/resources/"&gt;mobilise around these data&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;improve evidence-based practice, and save lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHO has produced a number of resources which can support timely action to prevent, diagnose and treat maternal infection, as well as activities such as the upcoming &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/infection-prevention/campaigns/clean-hands/en/"&gt;SAVE LIVES: Clean Your Hands&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;campaign
on 5 May which celebrates the central role played by nurses and midwives in clean health care.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition, WHO will publish a global sepsis epidemiology report around the 73rd World Health Assembly (WHA) in May, as requested in the
2017
&lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/gb/ebwha/pdf_files/WHA70/A70_R7-en.pdf"&gt;WHA Resolution on Improving the prevention, diagnosis and clinical managementof sepsis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding why and how infection affects women is essential for equipping healthcare providers with life-saving knowledge and enabling health care systems to bring down global maternal mortality and morbidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Related publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/186171/9789241549363_eng.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;WHO recommendations for prevention and treatment of maternal peripartum infections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/unsafe_abortion/clinical-practice-safe-abortion/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;WHO Clinical practice handbook for safe abortion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/infection-prevention/publications/ssi-guidelines/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;Global guidelines on the prevention of surgical site infection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/maternal_perinatal_health/maternalsepsis-statement/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;WHO statement on maternal sepsis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/gb/ebwha/pdf_files/WHA70/A70_R7-en.pdf?ua=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;World Health Assembly resolution on Improving the prevention, diagnosis and clinical management of sepsis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health Topics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/antimicrobial-resistance" data-auth="NotApplicable" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"&gt;Antimicrobial resistance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/infection-prevention/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;Infection Prevention and Control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;Water Sanitation Hygiene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://srhr.org/sepsis/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;Global Maternal Sepsis Study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/infection-prevention/campaigns/clean-hands/5may2020/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;SAVE LIVES: Clean Your Hands 5 May 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 22:35:08 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:a5fe834b-e7b2-49e9-9a63-14203efb9967</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/24-04-2020-global-leaders-unite-to-ensure-everyone-everywhere-can-access-new-vaccines-tests-and-treatments-for-covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Global leaders unite to ensure everyone everywhere can access new vaccines, tests and treatments for COVID-19</title><description>Heads of state and global health leaders today made an unprecedented commitment to work together to accelerate the development and production of new vaccines, tests and treatments for COVID-19 and assure equitable access worldwide.</description><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 14:58:24 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;Heads of state and global health leaders today made an unprecedented commitment to work together to accelerate the development and production of new vaccines, tests and treatments for COVID-19 and assure equitable access worldwide.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has already affected more than 2.4 million people, killing over 160,000. It is taking a huge toll on families, societies, health systems and economies around the world, and for as long as this virus threatens any country, the entire world is at risk.&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is an urgent need, therefore, while following existing measures to keep people physically distanced and to test and track all contacts of people who test positive, for innovative COVID-19 vaccines, diagnostics and treatments.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We will only halt COVID-19 through solidarity,&amp;rdquo; said Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, WHO Director-General. &amp;ldquo;Countries, health partners, manufacturers, and the private sector must act together and ensure that the fruits of science and research can benefit everybody.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work has already started. Since January, WHO has been working with researchers from hundreds of institutions to develop and test vaccines, standardize assays and standardize regulatory approaches on innovative trial designs and define criteria to prioritize vaccine candidates.&amp;nbsp; The Organization has prequalified diagnostics that are being used all over the world, and more are in the pipeline. And it is coordinating a global trial to assess the safety and efficacy of four therapeutics against COVID-19. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The challenge is to speed up and harmonize processes to ensure that once products are deemed safe and effective, they can be brought to the billions of people in the world who need them. Past experience, in the early days of HIV treatment, for example, and in the deployment of vaccines against the H1N1 outbreak in 2009, shows that even when tools are available, they have not been equally available to all. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So today leaders came together at a virtual event, co-hosted by the World Health Organization, the President of France, the President of the European Commission, and the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation. The event was joined by the UN Secretary General, the AU Commission Chairperson, the G20 President, heads of state of France, South Africa, Germany, Vietnam, Costa Rica, Italy, Rwanda, Norway, Spain, Malaysia and the UK (represented by the First Secretary of State).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health leaders from the Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI), GAVI-the Vaccine Alliance, the Global Fund, UNITAID, the Wellcome Trust, the International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement (IFRC), the International Federation of Pharmaceutical Manufacturers (IFPMA), the Developing Countries Vaccine Manufacturers&amp;rsquo; Network (DCVMN), and the International Generic and Biosimilar Medicines Association (IGBA) committed to come together, guided by a common vision of a planet protected from human suffering and the devastating social and economic consequences of COVID-19, to launch this groundbreaking collaboration. They are joined by two Special Envoys:&amp;nbsp; Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala, Gavi Board Chair and Sir Andrew Witty, former CEO of GlaxoSmithKline. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They pledged to work towards equitable global access based on an unprecedented level of partnership. They agreed to create a strong unified voice, to build on past experience and to be accountable to the world, to communities and to one another.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Our shared commitment is to ensure all people have access to all the tools to prevent, detect, treat and defeat COVID-19,&amp;rdquo; said Dr Tedros. &amp;ldquo;No country and no organization can do this alone. The Access to COVID-19 Tools Accelerator brings together the combined power of several organizations to work with speed and scale.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health leaders called on the global community and political leaders to support this landmark collaboration and for donors to provide the necessary resources to accelerate achievement of its objectives, capitalizing on the opportunity provided by a forthcoming pledging initiative that starts on 4 May 2020. This initiative, spearheaded by the European Union, aims to mobilize the significant resources needed to accelerate the work towards protecting the world from COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:f7106bf4-e9e9-4609-9237-bc4c7684e15e</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/24-04-2020-commitment-and-call-to-action-global-collaboration-to-accelerate-new-covid-19-health-technologies</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Commitment and call to action: Global collaboration to accelerate new COVID-19 health technologies</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our Vision and Mission&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grounded in a vision of a planet protected from human suffering
and the devastating social and economic consequences of
COVID-19, we, an initial group of global health actors (BMGF,
CEPI, Gavi, Global Fund, UNITAID, Wellcome Trust, WHO) and
private sector partners and other stakeholders, are launching
a landmark, global and time-limited collaboration to accelerate the
development, production and equitable global access to new COVID-19 essential health technologies.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We know that as long as anyone is at risk from this virus, the entire
world is at risk &amp;ndash; every single person on the planet needs to be
protected from this disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We agree that alongside evidence-based public health measures,
innovative COVID-19 diagnostics, therapeutics and vaccines are
needed &amp;ndash; in record time and at record scale and access &amp;ndash; to save
millions of lives and countless trillions of dollars, and to return
the world to a sense of &amp;lsquo;normalcy&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognize the significant amount of critical work, investment
and initiatives already ongoing around the world to expedite
the development and deployment of innovative COVID-19 related
products and interventions.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We appreciate that while development and deployment of
innovative products is essential, it will not be enough. We must
simultaneously and urgently accelerate the strengthening of
sustainable health systems and capacities to enable delivery of
the new COVID-19 tools to those who need them and to mitigate
the knock-on impact on other diseases.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We remember lessons from the past, which have shown that even
when effective tools are available to the world, too often some
are protected, while others are not. This inequity is unacceptable &amp;ndash;
all tools to address COVID-19 must be available to all. In the fight
against COVID-19, no one should be left behind.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We understand we cannot do this alone, and that we need to
work together in unprecedented and inclusive partnership with all
stakeholders &amp;ndash; political leaders, public and private sector partners,
civil society, academia, and all other stakeholders across society
&amp;ndash; jointly leveraging our comparative strengths and respective
voices to drive towards collective solutions, an accelerated path,
and access for all. We are stronger, faster and more effective
working together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our Mission is not only accelerated development and availability
of new COVID-19 tools &amp;ndash; it is to accelerate equitable global access
to safe, quality, effective, and affordable COVID-19 diagnostics,
therapeutics and vaccines, and thus to ensure that in the fight
against COVID-19, no one is left behind. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our Commitment&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;We commit to the shared aim of equitable global
access to innovative tools for COVID-19 for all.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We commit to an unprecedented level of partnership
&amp;ndash; proactively engaging stakeholders, aligning and
coordinating efforts, building on existing collaborations, collectively devising solutions, and grounding
our partnership in transparency, and science.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We commit to create a strong unified voice to
maximize impact, recognizing this is not about
singular decision-making authority, but rather
collective problem-solving, interconnectedness and
inclusivity, where all stakeholders can connect and
benefit from the expertise, knowledge and activities
of this shared action-oriented platform.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We commit to build on past experiences towards
achieving this objective, including ensuring that
every activity we undertake is executed through the
lens of equitable global access, and that the voices
of the communities most affected are heard.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We commit to be accountable to the world, to
communities, and to one another. We are coming
together in the spirit of solidarity, and in the service
of humanity, to achieve our mission and vision.  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our Call&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ask the global community and political leaders to
support this landmark collaboration, and for donors to
provide the necessary resources to accelerate achievement
of the objectives of this global collaboration, capitalizing
on the opportunity provided by the rolling pledging
campaign that will start on 4 May 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 14:51:56 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:451c995d-b9ad-4460-bb13-3335b6f3c814</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/23-04-2020-who-reports-fivefold-increase-in-cyber-attacks-urges-vigilance</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO reports fivefold increase in cyber attacks, urges vigilance</title><description>Since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic, WHO has seen a dramatic increase in the number of cyber attacks directed at its staff, and email scams targeting the public at large.</description><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 16:25:29 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic, WHO has seen a dramatic increase in the number of cyber attacks directed at its staff, and email scams targeting the public at large.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week, some 450 active WHO email addresses and passwords were leaked online along with thousands belonging to others working on the novel coronavirus response.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The leaked credentials did not put WHO systems at risk because the data was not recent. However, the attack did impact an older extranet system, used by current and retired staff as well as partners.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO is now migrating affected systems to a more secure authentication system.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scammers impersonating WHO in emails have also increasingly targeted the general public in order to channel donations to a fictitious fund and not the authentic &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/donate"&gt;COVID-19 Solidary Response Fund&lt;/a&gt;. The number of cyber attacks is now more than five times the number directed at the Organization in the same period last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ensuring the security of health information for Member States and the privacy of users interacting with us a priority for WHO at all times, but also particularly during the COVID-19 pandemic. We are grateful for the alerts we receive from Member States and the private sector. We are all in this fight together,&amp;rdquo;&amp;nbsp;said Bernardo Mariano, WHO&amp;rsquo;s Chief Information Officer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;WHO is working with the private sector to establish more robust internal systems and to strengthen security measures and is educating staff on cybersecurity risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO asks the public to remain vigilant against fraudulent emails and recommends the use of reliable sources to obtain factual information about COVID-19 and other health issues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information, please visit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a id="LPlnk250333" href="https://www.who.int/covid-19"&gt;www.who.int/covid-19&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:d8d23c82-fc88-4650-8fed-0ffc49a4cbaa</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/23-04-2020-infosan-quarterly-summary-2020-1</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>INFOSAN Quarterly Summary, 2020 #1</title><description>January-March 2020</description><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 15:04:09 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;font-size:25px;font-weight:700;text-align:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;Food safety incidents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the first quarter of 2020, the INFOSAN Secretariat was involved in 38 food safety incidents involving 109 WHO Member States and 9 territories of WHO Member States. There were 25 incidents involving a biological hazard (&lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; spp. [8], &lt;em&gt;Listeria monocytogenes&lt;/em&gt; [5], Norovirus [3] Shiga-toxin producing &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; [2], &lt;em&gt;Clostridium botulinum&lt;/em&gt; [2] &lt;em&gt;Bacillus cereus &lt;/em&gt;[2], &lt;em&gt;Cronobacter &lt;/em&gt;spp. [1], &lt;em&gt;Shigella sonnei&lt;/em&gt; [1], unspecified biological hazard [1]), 6 involving an undeclared allergen (milk [3], peanut (1), egg [1], gluten [1]), 5 involving a physical hazard (undetermined foreign matter [2], glass [1], metal [1], plastic [1]), one involving a chemical/toxin hazard (histamine), and one linked to an unspecified hazard. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The food categories that were most commonly involved in the 38 incidents during the first quarter of 2020 involved fish and other seafood (8), herbs and spices (4), legumes and pulses (4), milk and dairy products (3), nuts and oilseeds (3), snacks, desserts and other foods (3), cereals and cereal-based products (2), composite food (2), fruit and fruit products (2), meat and meat products (2), vegetables and vegetable products (2), products of special nutritional use (1), and food for infants and small children (1). One incident involved an unknown food source. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During such international food safety incidents, the INFOSAN Secretariat relies on the swift action of national INFOSAN Emergency Contact Points to respond to requests for information. Rapid sharing of information through INFOSAN enables members to implement appropriate risk management measures to prevent illness in their respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Geographic scope&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The outlined incidents involved Member States from all WHO regions: Europe (39), followed by the Americas (24), Africa (24), the Western Pacific (18), the Eastern Mediterranean (8) and South-East Asia (6). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recall in several countries of frozen spring roll sheets from Singapore due to the presence of an undeclared allergen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, the INFOSAN Secretariat was notified by the European Rapid Alert System for Food and Feed (RASFF) and INFOSAN colleagues in Australia of a recall in Australia and several European countries of frozen spring roll sheets due to the detection of an undeclared allergen (milk), imported from Singapore. In collaboration with &lt;a href="https://webgate.ec.europa.eu/rasff-window/portal/?event=notificationDetail&amp;amp;NOTIF_REFERENCE=2020.0715"&gt;RASFF&lt;/a&gt;, the INFOSAN Secretariat was informed that the implicated frozen spring roll sheets were distributed internationally to 46 Member States from four WHO regions and 4 territories in Europe and the Western Pacific. Moreover, through engagement with the INFOSAN Emergency Contact Point (ECP) in Singapore, the INFOSAN Secretariat also received details of further distribution of implicated products to additional WHO Member States from all WHO regions, taking the total number of Member States involved to 65. It was also reported that the products involved had been redistributed by some countries to Europe, the Americas and Africa. Consequently, several countries recalled the implicated products to relabel them and investigated the issue to identify illnesses related to the consumption of the implicated frozen spring roll sheets. No illnesses were reported to the INFOSAN Secretariat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This incident has highlighted undeclared allergens as an important category of hazards that can result in a largescale international response to implement risk management measures and prevent illness. In addition, it exemplified efficient communication among INFOSAN members and the Secretariat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outbreak of Listeriosis&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in the United States of America linked to enoki mushrooms imported from the Republic of Korea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, the INFOSAN Secretariat was made aware by the United States (US) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) of an outbreak of Listeriosis in the US linked to the consumption of enoki mushrooms, imported from the Republic of Korea. In total, 36 cases including 4 deaths have been &lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/food/outbreaks-foodborne-illness/outbreak-investigation-listeria-monocytogenes-enoki-mushrooms-march-2020"&gt;reported in the US&lt;/a&gt;. Following &lt;a href="https://healthycanadians.gc.ca/recall-alert-rappel-avis/inspection/2019/70475r-eng.php#affected-touches"&gt;investigations in Canada&lt;/a&gt;, carried out in collaboration with the US, the INFOSAN Secretariat was informed of 6 cases of Listeriosis between 2017 and 2019 in Canada potentially related by whole genome sequencing (WGS) to the ongoing outbreak in the USA. In addition, food isolates (from enoki mushrooms from the Republic of Korea) genetically associated with the cluster of cases have been collected in 2019 by authorities in Canada. The WGS information pertaining to the cases and food isolates were shared on the INFOSAN Community Website to assist the identification of cases in other countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The INFOSAN Secretariat engaged the INFOSAN Emergency Contact Point (ECP) in the Republic of Korea to seek details on any further international distribution of the implicated enoki mushrooms. Investigations are ongoing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;News &amp;amp; activities&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Sector and the COVID-19 outbreak&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 31 December 2019, WHO was alerted to several cases of pneumonia of unknown origin in the city of Wuhan, Hubei Province, China. The virus, a previously unknown coronavirus has been named SARS-CoV-2 and is the cause of the &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/surveillance-and-case-definitions"&gt;COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The WHO Epidemic Information Network (EPI-WIN) aims to share information tailored to specific sectors, including food and agriculture. The INFOSAN Secretariat has recently developed a guidance document for food businesses with regards to COVID-19 and food safety which is now available &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/covid-19-and-food-safety-guidance-for-food-businesses"&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. The guidance has also been disseminated through EPI-WIN and presented during two webinars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call for applicants: INFOSAN Train-the-Trainer Workshop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February, the INFOSAN Secretariat issued a call for applications for the INFOSAN Train-the-Trainer workshop. With the constant growth of the network, and the increased need for training that this entails, the INFOSAN Secretariat, in collaboration with the Canadian Food Inspection Agency (CFIA), has announced this workshop which aims to increase the human resources available to train INFOSAN members on a range of INFOSAN-related topics, online or in-person. As a result, it is expected that the understanding of the roles and responsibilities of INFOSAN members will be improved, resulting in greater participation that will enhance speed and efficiency during the response to food safety emergencies at the global level. The INFOSAN Secretariat, together with CFIA, look forward to hosting this important workshop later this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing the new INFOSAN Community Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The INFOSAN Community Website (ICW) continues to be an effective tool for the network to disseminate information during food safety emergencies. Over the past year, through the INFOSAN member survey, the Secretariat has gained a better understanding of how members use the ICW and how it can be improved to enhance information sharing. The information collected, together with the experience of members of the Secretariat, has provided numerous innovative ideas to guide the development of the new ICW. The Secretariat is pleased to announce that the competitive process to select the vendor that will develop the new INFOSAN Community Website has concluded and the work on the creation of the new ICW has begun.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Voice of an active network member&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.who.int/images/default-source/departments/fos/infosan/voice-5-2020.png?sfvrsn=c3133dde_4" alt="voice-5-2020" sf-size="94943" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:8102198d-946a-4dc4-9c41-82c33ef41225</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/23-04-2020-who-urges-countries-to-move-quickly-to-save-lives-from-malaria-in-sub-saharan-africa</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO urges countries to move quickly to save lives from malaria in sub-Saharan Africa</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Severe disruptions to insecticide-treated net campaigns and in access to antimalarial medicines could lead to a doubling in the number of malaria deaths in sub-Saharan Africa this year compared to 2018, according to a &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/the-potential-impact-of-health-service-disruptions-on-the-burden-of-malaria"&gt;new modelling analysis&lt;/a&gt; released by
    WHO and partners ahead of World Malaria Day (25 April).
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO urges countries to move fast and distribute malaria prevention and treatment tools at this stage of the COVID-19 outbreak in sub-Saharan Africa, and to do their utmost to safely maintain these essential malaria control services.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis considers nine scenarios for potential disruptions in access to core malaria control tools during the pandemic in 41 countries, and the resulting increases that may be seen in cases and deaths.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the worst-case scenario, in which all insecticide-treated net (ITN) campaigns are suspended and there is a 75% reduction in access to effective antimalarial medicines, the estimated tally of malaria deaths in sub-Saharan Africa in 2020 would reach
    769 000, twice the number of deaths reported in the region in 2018. This would represent a return to malaria mortality levels last seen 20 years ago.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;em&gt;World malaria report 2019&lt;/em&gt;, sub-Saharan Africa accounted for approximately 93% of all malaria cases and 94% of deaths in 2018. More than two-thirds of deaths were among children under the age of five.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A window of opportunity&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To date, the number of reported cases of COVID-19 in sub-Saharan Africa has represented only a small proportion of the global total, though cases are increasing every week. This means that countries across the region have a critical window of opportunity
    to minimize disruptions in malaria prevention and treatment and save lives at this stage of the COVID-19 outbreak.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mass vector control campaigns should be accelerated, while ensuring that they are deployed in ways that protect health workers and communities against potential COVID-19 transmission. WHO and partners commend the leaders of Benin, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, Sierra Leone and Chad
    for initiating ITN campaigns during the pandemic. Other countries are adapting their net distribution strategies to ensure households receive the nets as quickly and safely as possible.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preventive therapies for pregnant women and children must be maintained. The provision of prompt diagnostic testing and effective antimalarial medicines are also essential to prevent a mild case of malaria from progressing to severe illness and death.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO and partners have developed guidance to ensure that those suffering from malaria can safely receive the care they need within the package of essential health services to be delivered in COVID-19 settings. &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/malaria/areas/epidemics_emergencies/covid-19/en/"&gt;Tailoring malaria interventions in COVID-19 response&lt;/a&gt; includes guidance on the prevention of infection through vector control and chemoprevention, testing, treatment of cases, clinical services, supply chain and laboratory activities.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note to the editor&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The modelling analysis was conducted by WHO in close collaboration with partners, including PATH, the Malaria Atlas Project and the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis is subject to uncertainties. It does not consider, for example, the effects of an interruption in indoor residual spraying or seasonal malaria chemoprevention (except in Burkina Faso); a suspension of these core malaria prevention tools would
    also lead to considerable loss of life.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, there is limited understanding of the spread of COVID-19, its epidemiology and interactions with malaria. The model will be updated as such data become available, and countries will be provided with relevant information to tailor their responses
    accordingly.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 14:17:13 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:233bdaae-f04d-4455-ba8e-cf30f0f54f34</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/23-04-2020-hard-fought-gains-in-immunization-coverage-at-risk-without-critical-health-services-warns-who</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Hard fought gains in immunization coverage at risk without critical health services, warns WHO</title><description>Shutting down immunization services in the COVID-19 pandemic risks triggering a resurgence of diseases that can be prevented with safe and effective vaccines, warns WHO in the lead-up to World Immunization Week (24-30 April).</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 22:01:47 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;Shutting down immunization services in the COVID-19 pandemic risks triggering a resurgence of diseases that can be prevented with safe and effective vaccines, warns WHO in the lead-up to &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/campaigns/world-immunization-week/world-immunization-week-2020"&gt;World Immunization Week&lt;/a&gt; (24-30 April).&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When immunization services are disrupted, even for brief periods during emergencies, the risk of vaccine-preventable disease outbreaks, such as measles and polio, increase. Last&amp;nbsp;year&amp;rsquo;s deadly measles outbreak in the Democratic Republic of the
    Congo, which took more than 6000 lives in a country already facing its largest Ebola outbreak, highlights the importance of maintaining essential health services, such as immunization in times of emergency. Further disease outbreaks will also overwhelm
    health systems already battling the impacts of COVID-19.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Disease outbreaks must not remain a threat when we have safe and effective vaccines to protect us,&amp;rdquo; said Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, WHO Director-General. &amp;ldquo;While the world strives to develop a new vaccine for COVID-19 at record speed,
    we must not risk losing the fight to protect everyone, everywhere against&amp;nbsp;vaccine-preventable diseases. These diseases will come roaring back if we do not vaccinate.&amp;rdquo;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO is working with partners all over the world to accelerate research and development&amp;nbsp;of a safe and effective vaccine and&amp;nbsp;ensure equitable access&amp;nbsp;for the billions of people who will need it.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even with an expedited process, development of a vaccine for COVID-19 will take time. Precautionary measures are essential now to help keep us safe from disease, including diseases for which vaccines already protect children and adults.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Too many people are still excluded from the benefits of vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to the COVID-19 pandemic, the world had made immense progress in ensuring that children are vaccinated. In 2018, 86 percent of children under the age of five globally were vaccinated with three doses of diphtheria, tetanus and pertussis (DTP3) and
    one dose of the measles vaccine, up from 72 percent in 2000 and 20 percent in 1980. The number of children paralyzed by polio has been reduced by 99.9 percent worldwide.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yet, global vaccination coverage is still far from the 95 per cent coverage needed to fully protect communities against outbreaks of this vaccine-preventable disease.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2018 nearly 20 million children worldwide &amp;ndash; more than 1 in 10 &amp;ndash; missed out on lifesaving vaccines, such as measles, diphtheria and tetanus. Roughly, 13 million of the children have never received any vaccines, putting them and their communities
    at risk of disease and death. The majority of these children live in countries with already fragile health systems, further limiting their access to essential health services when they fall sick.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Measles continues to remain an ever-present threat, especially if vaccination rates drops. Current projections indicate that the number of reported measles cases for 2019 will be at least 800 000. In 2020 there are increasing concerns about another
    resurgence, especially if vaccination rates fall due to delay or suspension of scheduled immunization activities as a result of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outbreaks of polio, diphtheria and yellow fever are also of high concern, especially in the countries least able to respond quickly and decisively to address an emerging outbreak, as seen in previous emergencies such as the polio outbreak in Syria in
    2013.&amp;nbsp;
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Maintaining immunization services during COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As&amp;nbsp;the response to&amp;nbsp;COVID-19&amp;nbsp;continues, countries must&amp;nbsp;act now&amp;nbsp;protect immunization services, in order to further minimize disease outbreaks and loss of life. This includes, facilitating urgent catch up programmes in places where
    services have been disrupted, ensuring strong supply chains, disease surveillance and trained health workers. Caregivers should also make sure they continue to vaccinate their children in line with national policies.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;New &lt;a href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/331590/WHO-2019-nCoV-immunization_services-2020.1-eng.pdf"&gt;WHO guidelines on immunization and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; recommend that governments temporarily pause preventive immunization
    campaigns where there is no active outbreak of a vaccine-preventable disease.&amp;nbsp;But it urges countries prioritize the continuation of routine immunization of children in essential service delivery, as well as adult vaccinations such as influenza
    for groups most at risk. If immunization services must be suspended, urgent catch-up vaccinations should be rescheduled as soon as possible, prioritizing those most at risk.
    &lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:336d6ac7-601b-4b35-8788-befd4312f04b</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/22-04-2020-what-matters-to-women-in-the-postnatal-period</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>What matters to women in the postnatal period?</title><description>&lt;h2&gt;The right to a positive maternity healthcare experience at every stage&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each pregnancy is unique and clinical needs can change across the pregnancy, childbirth and postnatal periods. One thing that never changes is the right to a positive experience at every stage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Achieving the best possible physical, emotional, and psychological outcomes for every individual and newborn requires health systems to take a human rights-based approach: not only preventing maternal death and morbidity, but prioritising person-centred
    care and well-being.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO is developing new guidelines for a positive experience of postnatal care, due to be published next year. To inform these guidelines and ensure that postnatal services can better meet the needs of women and their babies, WHO undertook a qualitative
    systematic review on &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0231415"&gt;what matters to women in the postnatal period&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Joys and challenges in the postnatal period&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is limited research about values and preferences in the postnatal period, defined by WHO as the first six weeks after childbirth. Studies have often focused on the results of specific postnatal interventions, rather than on the individuals who use
    them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0231415"&gt;What matters to women in the postnatal period: A meta-synthesis of qualitative studies&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rsquo; published in PLOS ONE, gives long-overdue respect to the authority of women&amp;rsquo;s own experiences. The authors review first-hand data from 15 countries
    and 36 studies published after the year 2000 relating to women&amp;rsquo;s beliefs, expectations and values at this significant time of life.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These studies affirm that a positive postnatal experience can result in joy, self-confidence and enhanced capacity to thrive as both a person and a parent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are also vocal about the potential challenges of adjusting to a &amp;lsquo;new normal&amp;rsquo; following childbirth, including changes in self-identity, relationships, and sexual behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What is a positive postnatal experience?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A positive postnatal experience for a woman will be one that responds to her specific context and preferences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will provide the confidence, knowledge and skills women need in the weeks following childbirth, supporting them to adjust to any changes in their intimate relationships and build new family ones. Women will be better equipped to navigate physical and
    emotional challenges and to experience the dynamic achievement of personal growth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This should be a shared responsibility, not a solitary one. Community has a critical role in enabling a positive postnatal experience, including partners, family and elders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is crucial that healthcare providers meet each woman&amp;rsquo;s needs, as well as those of their babies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Supporting choices and rights to improve postnatal health outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are an estimated 303 000 maternal deaths annually, &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/maternal-mortality-2000-2017/en/"&gt;according to recent WHO figures&lt;/a&gt;. Most of these deaths occur postnatally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The postnatal period is therefore a vital opportunity to improve both maternal and neonatal health and wellbeing: supporting healthy behaviors, providing life-skills education, facilitating breastfeeding, counselling women about family planning options,
    supporting good mental health, preventing and treating childbirth-related complications.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health care systems that empower individuals by supporting their values, preferences and rights are fundamental to improving maternal and newborn health outcomes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;WHO&amp;rsquo;s guidance for positive maternity care&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO has recently released recommendations on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/maternal_perinatal_health/anc-positive-pregnancy-experience/en/"&gt;antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;and on&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/intrapartum-care-guidelines/en/"&gt;intrapartum care for a positive childbirth experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These publications made important clinical updates, including an increase from four to eight recommended antenatal contacts, and a revision to the decision-making process for interventions to accelerate labour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They also uphold every woman&amp;rsquo;s right to a positive maternity care experience: one where her pregnancy does not erase her competency, autonomy and right to participate in decision-making for her own care and the care of her newborn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women&amp;rsquo;s choices and rights to sexual and reproductive health care, including maternity care, should be respected at every stage of the continuum of maternal and newborn care. This is true across all income settings, as well as in humanitarian settings
    and during public health emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When WHO&amp;rsquo;s postnatal guidelines are released next year, they will complete the maternity care series built around what matters to women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rather than dividing care into three periods of antenatal, intrapartum and postnatal, these publications can be used to establish a model in which health systems support women, their baby and wider network physically, psychologically, socially and emotionally
    through this significant life event.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Other resources&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/maternal_perinatal_health/anc-positive-pregnancy-experience/en/"&gt;WHO recommendations on antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/intrapartum-care-guidelines/en/"&gt;WHO recommendations: intrapartum care for a positive childbirth experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/improving-early-childhood-development-who-guideline"&gt;Improving early childhood development: WHO guideline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/healthy-parenting"&gt;Parenting in the time of COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/q-a-on-covid-19-pregnancy-childbirth-and-breastfeeding"&gt;Q&amp;amp;A on COVID-19, pregnancy, childbirth and breastfeeding&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/clinical-management-of-severe-acute-respiratory-infection-when-novel-coronavirus-(ncov)-infection-is-suspected"&gt;Clinical management of severe acute respiratory infection when COVID-19 is suspected&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/mistreatment-of-women-during-childbirth/en/"&gt;Evidence on mistreatment of women during childbirth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/breastfeeding#tab=tab_1"&gt;Related topic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/breastfeeding#tab=tab_1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/breastfeeding#tab=tab_1"&gt;Breastfeeding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 18:04:54 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:c1701d8a-0f84-484e-970f-516695af7d83</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/20-04-2020-joint-statement-by-wto-director-general-roberto-azev%C3%AAdo-and-who-director-general-tedros-adhanom-ghebreyesus</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Joint statement by WTO Director-General Roberto Azevêdo and WHO Director-General Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus</title><description>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has rapidly progressed to become a global pandemic, causing unprecedented, far-reaching impact on the health, social and economic well-being of communities around the world. The World Health Organization (WHO) and World Trade Organization (WTO) are committed to responding effectively to the situation, working together with other&amp;nbsp;international organizations and our respective memberships. Global, coordinated action is required to deal with the extraordinary challenges the pandemic poses to people&amp;rsquo;s health as well as their livelihoods.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Protecting lives is our top priority, and these efforts can be impeded by unnecessary disruptions to global trade and supply chains. Governments&amp;rsquo; trade policy decisions significantly influence both getting medical equipment and supplies to where they are urgently needed and catalyzing the supply of critical inputs for the production of medicines and health technologies to fight the pandemic. Keeping trade in health technologies as open and predictable as possible is therefore of vital interest. This will help countries to respond to this crisis, to recover from it and to build the health systems that will foster greater resilience in the future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;WHO and WTO are working together to support efforts to ensure the normal cross-border flow of vital medical supplies and other goods and services, promoting them where possible, and to resolve unnecessary disruptions to global supply chains, in furtherance of the International Health Regulations (2005) and WTO rules.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The purpose of the International Health Regulations is to prevent, protect against, control and provide a public health response to the international spread of disease in ways that are commensurate with public health risks, with a view to minimizing interference with international traffic and trade.&amp;nbsp;WTO rules provide governments with the flexibilities they may need to address essential medical supply shortages and/or public health challenges. But any measure taken to promote public health that restricts trade should be &amp;ldquo;targeted, proportionate, transparent and temporary&amp;rdquo;, consistent with recent calls from world leaders.&amp;nbsp; Governments need to avoid measures that can disrupt supply chains and negatively impact the poorest and most vulnerable, notably in developing and least developed countries that are typically reliant on imports of medicines and medical equipment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We call on our Members&amp;nbsp;to continue to share information about their measures with WHO and WTO, in line with the established transparency mechanisms, which are now especially valuable in supporting a coordinated response. To ensure that health technologies, including diagnostics, medicines, vaccines and other medical supplies vital to treating patients infected by COVID-19, reach those in need quickly, we emphasize the importance of streamlining conformity checks based on regulatory cooperation and international standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While we are heartened by the remarkable research efforts and the rapid mobilization of public and private resources to develop COVID-19 health technologies, we&amp;nbsp;call upon governments to implement policy measures that can further facilitate their research and development, and to promote their rapid dissemination within countries and across borders so as to ensure equitable access to those technologies. Such initiatives include targeted investment, ensuring open access to clinical test results, the sharing of relevant intellectual property rights, increasing manufacturing capacity, open and transparent procurement regimes, the elimination of tariffs on relevant health technologies, and trade facilitation measures to reduce costs and delays.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Global action, solidarity and international cooperation are more necessary than ever to address this health situation.&amp;nbsp; WHO and the WTO are working together to play their part.​&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 17:07:23 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:b04471b7-061d-4806-9309-2adc27cd5420</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/20-04-2020-un-agencies-issue-urgent-call-to-fund-the-global-emergency-supply-system-to-fight-covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>UN agencies issue urgent call to fund the global emergency supply system to fight COVID-19</title><description>The heads of the United Nations’ major agencies have issued a warning of the risk of COVID-19 to the world’s most vulnerable countries. International donors have pledged around a quarter of the US$2 billion the UN requested in the Global Humanitarian Response Plan for COVID-19 in March.</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 17:06:46 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;The heads of the United Nations&amp;rsquo; major agencies have issued a warning of the risk of&amp;nbsp;COVID-19 to the world&amp;rsquo;s most vulnerable countries. International donors&amp;nbsp;have pledged around a quarter of the US$2 billion
                            the UN requested in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.unocha.org/sites/unocha/files/Global-Humanitarian-Response-Plan-COVID-19.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;Global Humanitarian&amp;nbsp;Response Plan for COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in
 March.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Following is the text of the open letter:&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;Dear donor community,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Humanity is collectively facing its most daunting challenge since the Second World War.&amp;nbsp;COVID-19&amp;nbsp;knows
                            no borders, spares no country or continent, and strikes indiscriminately. By&amp;nbsp;all accounts, we are at least 12 months away from a vaccine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In this race against an invisible enemy, all countries must fight back,
                            but not all begin from the&amp;nbsp;same starting line. In countries where the world&amp;rsquo;s most vulnerable need humanitarian aid and&amp;nbsp;supplies to beat back the pandemic, cancelled flights and disrupted supply routes hit&amp;nbsp;disproportionately
                            hard. It is in everyone&amp;rsquo;s interest to stop the virus from spreading unchecked,&amp;nbsp;destroying lives and economies, and continuing to circle around the world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.unocha.org/story/un-issues-2-billion-appeal-combat-covid-19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-auth="NotApplicable"&gt;UN Secretary-General on 25 March launched&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;the COVID-19 Global Humanitarian&amp;nbsp;Response Plan, requesting US$2 billion to boost the global response.
                            You have been fast and&amp;nbsp;generous in your funding and have extended lifelines to those who were already caught up in&amp;nbsp;war, poverty and the worst effects of climate change &amp;ndash; especially at a time when your own&amp;nbsp;populations
                            are suffering from the impact of the virus.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Around $550 million has generously been made available to implement the Plan so far, with&amp;nbsp;significant additional resources being mobilized and pledged.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The
 Central Emergency Response Fund (CERF) has also released $95 million to kick-start the&amp;nbsp;COVID-19 response, help contain the spread of the virus, maintain supply chains, and provide&amp;nbsp;assistance and protection to the
                            most vulnerable people, including women and girls, refugees&amp;nbsp;and internally displaced persons. But more needs to be done.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To get more deliveries off the ground, the UN World Food Programme (WFP) is setting up
                            the&amp;nbsp;vital logistics backbone that will help save lives and help halt the spread of the virus. WFP now&amp;nbsp;urgently needs additional funding to establish the necessary transport hubs, charter vessels&amp;nbsp;and provide aircraft
                            for cargo, health workers and other essential staff.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;All elements of the Global Humanitarian Response Plan are crucial and need continued&amp;nbsp;funding, but without these logistics common services, the global response
                            could stutter to a&amp;nbsp;halt. Now is not the time to slow down. No one is safe until everyone is safe.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We, humanitarian organizations from across the world, therefore, call upon you to urgently&amp;nbsp;support this
                            global emergency supply system with an initial $350 million to enable a rapid&amp;nbsp;scale-up of logistics common services.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These services, which WFP provides on behalf of the entire global humanitarian community,&amp;nbsp;will
                            enable a swift, efficient response to COVID-19 for the most vulnerable people. Any delay in&amp;nbsp;our action could undermine global efforts to bring the pandemic under control.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The scale-up of the COVID-19 services
                            includes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Establishing, equipping and managing international consolidation hubs and regional&amp;nbsp;staging areas.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Air and shipping cargo services.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Passenger air services, with the necessary measures to avoid further spreading of the&amp;nbsp;virus.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Medical evacuation services for front-line workers.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Infrastructure and construction of treatment centres.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Real-time remote data collection.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull; Critical investments required to safely deliver operations and services.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever it takes, we as humanitarians are determined to meet people&amp;rsquo;s urgent needs. The&amp;nbsp;upscaling of the common services that we all depend on is crucial to enable us to meet these&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Every human
                            being, in every nation around the world, is facing the same mortal threat. Every&amp;nbsp;step that speeds delivery, saves lives. The COVID-19 pandemic has presented all of humanity&amp;nbsp;with a unique challenge, and only a uniquely
                            global response can halt its forward march.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now is the time to step up together, to prevent needless suffering, and to fulfil the promise of a&amp;nbsp;better future for all.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We hope to hear from you soon.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Mark Lowcock&lt;/strong&gt;, Emergency Relief Coordinator and Under-Secretary-General for&amp;nbsp;Humanitarian Affairs, Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Filippo Grandi&lt;/strong&gt;,
 United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, United Nations Refugee&amp;nbsp;Agency (UNHCR)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ms. Henrietta H. Fore&lt;/strong&gt;, Executive Director, United Nations Children&amp;rsquo;s Fund (UNICEF)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. David Beasley&lt;/strong&gt;,
 Executive Director, United Nations World Food Programme (WFP)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Achim Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;, Administrator, United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus&lt;/strong&gt;,
 Director-General, United Nations World Health&amp;nbsp;Organization (WHO)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Qu Dongyu&lt;/strong&gt;, Director-General, United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Ant&amp;oacute;nio Vitorino&lt;/strong&gt;,
 Director-General, United Nations International Organization for&amp;nbsp;Migration (IOM)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Natalia Kanem&lt;/strong&gt;, Executive Director, United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ms. Michelle Bachelet&lt;/strong&gt;,
 High Commissioner, United Nations Office of the High Commissioner&amp;nbsp;for Human Rights (OHCHR)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Gareth Price-Jones&lt;/strong&gt;, Executive Secretary, Steering Committee for Humanitarian&amp;nbsp;Response (SCHR)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Ignacio Packer&lt;/strong&gt;, Executive Director, International Council of Voluntary Agencies (ICVA)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Sam Worthington&lt;/strong&gt;, President and CEO, InterAction&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ms. Cecilia Jimenez-Damary&lt;/strong&gt;,
 Special Rapporteur on the human rights of internally displaced&amp;nbsp;persons, United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights (OHCHR)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr. Jagan Chapagain&lt;/strong&gt;, Secretary General, International
                            Federation of Red Cross and Red&amp;nbsp;Crescent Societies (IFRC)&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:19952f9d-08d4-4a17-b0f1-0856a1cf352d</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/20-04-2020-itu-who-joint-statement-unleashing-information-technology-to-defeat-covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>ITU-WHO Joint Statement: Unleashing information technology to defeat COVID-19</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The World Health Organization, the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) with support from UNICEF are set to work with telecommunication companies to text people directly on their mobile phones with vital health messaging to help protect them from COVID-19. These text messages will reach billions of people that aren&amp;rsquo;t able to connect to the internet for information. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, technology must ensure that everyone can access the information they need. The collaboration will start in the Asia Pacific region and then roll out globally. The goal is to reach everyone with vital health messages, whatever their connectivity level. An estimated 3.6 billion people remain offline, with most people who are unconnected living in low-income countries, where an average of just two out of every ten people are online. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ITU and WHO call on all telecommunication companies worldwide to join this initiative to help unleash the power of communication technology to save lives from COVID-19. This initiative builds on current efforts to disseminate health messages through the joint WHO-ITU BeHealthy BeMobile initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) is the first pandemic in human history where technology and social media are being used on a massive scale to keep people safe, productive and connected while being physically apart. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health workers are utilizing telemedicine to diagnose patients and hospitals rely on being connected to coordinate and triage them. Resilient and trustworthy telecommunication networks and services are essential, as more countries, companies and individuals turn to digital technologies to respond to and cope with the impact of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building on their longstanding collaboration, ITU and WHO are committed to identifying and scaling best evidence-based digital health solutions and to leveraging frontier technologies such as artificial intelligence and big data to diagnose, contain and predict outbreaks better and faster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The World Health Organization provides global leadership in public health within the United Nations system. Founded in 1948, WHO works with 194 Member States, across six regions and from more than 150 offices, to promote health, keep the world safe and serve the vulnerable. Our goal for 2019-2023 is to ensure that a billion more people have universal health coverage, to protect a billion more people from health emergencies, and provide a further billion people with better health and wellbeing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For updates on COVID-19 and public health advice to protect yourself from coronavirus, visit&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/home"&gt;www.who.int&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and follow WHO on&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WHO"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/WHO/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/who/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/world-health-organization/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@who"&gt;&lt;em&gt;TikTok&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pinterest.ch/worldhealthorganization/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pinterest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.snapchat.com/add/whorg"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snapchat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/WHO"&gt;&lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;International Telecommunication Union (ITU)&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;A specialized United Nations agency for information and communication technologies (ICTs), driving innovation in ICTs together with 193 Member States and a membership of over 900 companies, universities, and international and regional organizations. Established over 150 years ago in 1865, ITU is responsible for coordinating the shared global use of the radio spectrum, promoting international cooperation in assigning satellite orbits, improving communication infrastructure in the developing world, and establishing the worldwide standards that foster seamless interconnection of a vast range of communications systems. For more information, visit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.itu.int/"&gt;www.itu.int&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 10:27:41 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:4d6fe70e-140c-4cd3-a028-3860c8a401a0</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/20-04-2020-who-guidance-helps-detect-iron-deficiency-and-protect-brain-development</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO guidance helps detect iron deficiency and protect brain development</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Detecting iron deficiency early during pregnancy and in young children is crucial. Iron deficiency in children under two years of age can have significant and irreversible effects on brain development. This can lead to negative consequences on learning and school performance later in life. Cognitive development of a child can also be affected if a mother is iron deficient during her last trimester of pregnancy. New &lt;em&gt;World Health Organization guidelines on the use of ferritin concentrations to assess iron status in individuals and populations&lt;/em&gt; will help health workers to detect iron deficiency early and avoid the most severe impacts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO shows how to best measure ferritin, an indicator of iron stores, to help determine iron deficiency or overload. Ferritin is a protein which can be found in small amounts circulating in a person&amp;rsquo;s blood. Ferritin levels are low in iron-deficient individuals and high in iron-loaded individuals. Accurate measurements of this protein, along with clinical and laboratory evaluation, can guide the appropriate interventions in both individual patients and at a population level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Reducing anemia is one of the components of our efforts to eradicate all forms of malnutrition. However, progress has been limited and we still have 614 million women and 280 million children globally who suffer from it,&amp;rdquo; said Dr Francesco Branca, Director of the Department of Nutrition and Food Safety at WHO. &amp;ldquo;Iron deficiency is a major determinant of anemia and measuring ferritin, a key biomarker of iron metabolism, will help us better target and evaluate our action to fight anemia&amp;rdquo; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iron is an essential element with important functions such as oxygen transport, DNA synthesis and muscle metabolism. Iron deficiency is the main cause of anaemia, which is the most prevalent nutritional deficiency worldwide, affecting 33% of non-pregnant women, 40% of pregnant women, and 42% of children worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;In adults, iron deficiency can also have negative effects including fatigue, impaired physical performance and decreased work productivity, as well as impacting social activities. Iron deficiency occurs mainly when the requirements of iron increase during rapid periods of growth and development such as in early childhood, adolescence and pregnancy, but it can occur at other stages in life. In pregnant women, iron deficiency can cause anaemia, reduced birth weight and reduced gestation periods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;The new guidelines also cover the early detection of iron overload. Iron overload (accumulation of iron in the body) is generally the result of disorders such as hereditary haemochromatosis, thalassaemia, repeated blood transfusions or other conditions that affect iron absorption or regulation and can also lead to deterioration of a person&amp;rsquo;s health if left untreated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;Improved knowledge about the prevalence and distribution of iron deficiency and risk of iron overload in the population helps countries to decide on appropriate interventions, and to monitor and evaluate the impact and safety of public health programmes. For example, nutritional iron deficiency can be commonly found in populations that also have infectious diseases. The adequate evaluation of iron status in countries with infectious disorders can help countries to put in place adequate health policies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;The WHO guidelines aim to help WHO Member States and their partners to make evidence-informed decisions on appropriate actions in their efforts to lower iron deficiency and improve the health and quality of life of individuals and populations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;For interviews with WHO technical experts, please contact: Pippa HAUGHTON &amp;ndash; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:haughtonp@who.int" style="text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;haughtonp@who.int&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt; +41794466331&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To access a copy of the full guidelines, please &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/9789240000124"&gt;visit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 22:05:07 Z</pubDate></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:0d9ea6f3-87d1-41e1-915d-606e0dc828d5</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/20-04-2020-who-advisory-body-releases-malaria-eradication-report</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO advisory body releases malaria eradication report</title><description>After a 3-year study of trends and future projections, the WHO Strategic Advisory Group on Malaria Eradication (SAGme) has released a detailed report of its findings and recommendations.</description><pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 08:53:29 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p&gt;After a 3-year study of trends and future projections, the WHO Strategic Advisory Group on Malaria Eradication (SAGme) has released a &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/malaria-eradication-benefits-future-scenarios-feasibility"&gt;detailed report&lt;/a&gt; of its findings and recommendations. The report builds and expands on an &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/strategic-advisory-group-malaria-eradication-executive-summary"&gt;executive summary&lt;/a&gt; published in August 2019.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Established in 2016 at the request of the former WHO Director-General, Dr Margaret Chan, SAGme was tasked with analysing future scenarios for malaria, including the feasibility of eradication. Its members commissioned analyses and consulted widely with
    malaria and global health experts throughout their tenure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the new report, SAGme reaffirms the WHO vision of a world free of malaria &amp;ndash; a goal enshrined in World Health Assembly resolutions dating back to 1955. There is a consensus that eradicating malaria would result in millions of lives saved and generate
    a substantial return on investment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ridding the world of a parasite that overwhelmingly affects the poor and vulnerable would be a remarkable step towards global health equity and improved economic conditions in the poorest parts of the world,&amp;rdquo; says the 13-member group of eminent
    public health leaders. &amp;ldquo;The SAGme unequivocally supports this goal.&amp;rdquo;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, members of the advisory body recognize that the goal of eradication is still far from reach. &amp;ldquo;Even with our most optimistic scenarios and projections, we face an unavoidable fact: using current tools, we will still have 11 million cases
    of malaria in Africa in 2050,&amp;rdquo; they conclude.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;&lt;em style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;"WHO continues to unequivocally support the goal of malaria eradication. To achieve this vision, we must deliver on our promises: to increase domestic and international investments in health; reduce malaria in the highest-burden countries; achieve universal health coverage; ensure no child dies from a preventable disease; and leave no one behind in pursuit of health and development goals because they were born poor. By delivering on these promises and investing in the development of transformative new tools, the world can achieve the health-related Sustainable Development Goals and eradicate malaria."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;WHO Director General, Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;font-size:25px;font-weight:700;text-align:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;Key findings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SAGme considered a broad set of factors that underpin malaria: biological, technical, financial, socio-economic, political, and environmental. Its members reviewed trends in poverty and population growth, mobility, agricultural development, climate change,
    and urbanization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group also analyzed likely threats to malaria eradication, including health emergencies, and concluded that while epidemics may cause short-term setbacks, malaria eradication could still be achieved. They examined the impact of global governance mechanisms,
    health system readiness, community engagement, and other disease eradication efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After reviewing the findings of numerous analyses and debating the conclusions, SAGme identified 6 areas that would shore up a successful malaria eradication effort.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reinforcing the global strategy: &lt;/strong&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Global technical strategy for malaria 2016-2030 &lt;/em&gt;provides a comprehensive and flexible framework to guide countries in their efforts to control and eliminate malaria, it will require some refinement and updating to lay a strong foundation for the eventual launch of a time-limited eradication campaign.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research &amp;amp; development for new tools:&lt;/strong&gt; Although existing tools have achieved remarkable impact, the world currently lacks the transformative tools needed to achieve malaria elimination in the highest burden areas. One of the highest priorities for achieving a world free of malaria is a renewed research and development agenda that improves the knowledge base and products necessary for achieving eradication.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access to affordable, high quality, people-centered health care and services:&lt;/strong&gt; To eliminate malaria and contribute towards global eradication, a country requires strong political commitment and investment in universal health care, with a well-functioning primary health care system at its base. Health system quality is strongly correlated with malaria progress across the spectrum of malaria endemicity.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adequate and sustained financing:&lt;/strong&gt; Since 2010, global funding for malaria control and elimination has remained relatively stagnant at around US$ 3 billion per year, despite an estimated need of US$ 6.4 billion per year to meet the 2020 targets of the global strategy. Financing must be adequate and sustained to support countries to reduce the burden of malaria and achieve elimination.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthened surveillance and response:&lt;/strong&gt; Surveillance and response systems must be nimble, reliable, rapid and accurate to react to changing social and physical environments and provide data to drive better decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engaging communities:&lt;/strong&gt; Communities play an essential role in the push towards a malaria-free world.&amp;nbsp; Affected communities must be effectively engaged in co-planning, co-implementing and co-evaluating malaria programme services and interventions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;font-size:25px;font-weight:700;text-align:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;Laying a foundation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;SAGme members recognize that the world is currently off track to meet critical 2025 targets of the &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/global-technical-strategy-for-malaria-2016-2030" style="font-family:Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:16px;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;" target="_blank"&gt;global malaria strategy&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;span style="background-color:transparent;font-family:Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:16px;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt; &amp;ndash; reductions of at least 75% in malaria morbidity and mortality compared to 2015 levels. They note that achieving the targets of the global strategy must be the first step in a &amp;ldquo;pragmatic, strategic and humanitarian approach&amp;rdquo;
            toward the longer-term goal of eradication.&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;National ownership of malaria elimination efforts, they say, is essential. &amp;ldquo;Countries must move under their own direction while being supported and encouraged by WHO and partners to progress as quickly as possible towards elimination and, eventually,
    eradication.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:e032b0e4-6bd9-4dba-b952-e15f77618915</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/17-04-2020-eradicating-dracunculiasis-ethiopia-investigates-six-suspected-human-cases-in-gambella-region</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>Eradicating dracunculiasis: Ethiopia investigates six suspected human cases in Gambella region</title><description>In 2019, Ethiopia and Mali reported zero human cases of dracunculiasis (guinea-worm disease), although the total number of human cases reported to the World Health Organization (WHO) last year peaked at 54 cases.
While surveillance activities have been stepped-up in countries reporting cases, hundreds more field workers and volunteers are being trained, and, cross-border vigilance are being carried out to prevent transmission.</description><pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 16:22:19 Z</pubDate><a10:content type="text">&lt;p class="section_head1"&gt;&amp;nbsp;After reporting zero human cases 
for more than two years, Ethiopia has recorded six suspected new human 
cases&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; of dracunculiasis (guinea-worm disease) over the past two weeks. All of them are from Gog district in the region of Gambella. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;All
 the six suspected new cases of infection are people who used water from
 farm side-ponds and all of them are now being followed-up in a 
containment centre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;rdquo; said Dr Zeyede Kebede, Acting NTD Programme Coordinator, WHO Country Office, Ethiopia. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Four
 of the suspected cases were detected from Dulli farm side village and 
two others from two different villages namely - Metaget Dipach and 
Wadmaro in Gog Dipach Kebele&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Besides
 the six-suspected new infection, a further 40 suspected cases are also 
being followed up in the Guinea Worm Case Containment Center. 
Furthermore, an estimated 200 households have been visited and 1254 
people interviewed and provided with health education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The
 Ethiopian Dracunculiasis Eradication Programme (EDEP) is scheduled to 
continue the larviciding of ponds in the area; further assess the 
utilization of filters by residents and devise a mechanism to maximize 
and maintain its utilization. The EDEP also plans to work with relevant 
stakeholders to provide safe water to the villages with suspected cases.





&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Despite
 redeployment of health staff due to COVID-19, response to this outbreak
 was swift and in accordance with established protocols&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; said Mr Kassahun Demissie, National Programme Coordinator for Guinea Worm Eradication, Ethiopian Public Health Institute. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Preliminary
 investigations were carried out and immediate intervention measures 
taken, including active case search in seven villages where the 
suspected cases were detected and in nearby at-risk villages&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other measures that have been immediately implemented include:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;treatment of more than 41 ponds in the vicinity with the larvicide Temephos&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. This is in addition to the regular cycle of larviciding of all ponds in the area;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;assessment of water filter utilization and their replacement;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;delivery of health education in all villages that were visited.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A
 visit is also scheduled to the region by WHO&amp;rsquo;s National Programme 
Officer and the acting National Coordinator from 24 April to 1 May to 
monitor containment and prevention activities and provide overall 
support as part of outbreak response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Dracunculiasis eradication in Ethiopia&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since
 Ethiopia established its national dracunculiasis eradication programme 
in 1994 considerable progress has been made to reduce the number of 
human cases, with most of them focused in Gambella. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For
 the past decade, the region consistently reported low level 
transmission, including few infections in animals. In 2019, health and 
rural development officials in the region announced a series of measures
 aimed at ending transmission of dracunculiasis. It included a 
high-level advocacy mission led by the Federal Minister of Health and 
the announcement of a Board to oversee the functioning of the 
eradication programme in the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To
 increase the sensitivity of the surveillance system, the authorities 
have also introduced a cash reward for the voluntary reporting of 
dracunculiasis cases.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Human cases in 2019&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;In
 2019, a total of 54 human cases were reported to WHO, with Chad 
reporting 48 out of the 54 cases. Chad is also reporting a high number 
of animal infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The
 other three countries that reported human cases last year were Angola 
(1 case) and South Sudan (4 cases), and Cameroon (1 case which is likely
 a spillover from neighbouring endemic villages in Chad). Mali, where 
animal infections are occurring, has not reported any human case since 
2016.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;The disease&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dracunculiasis is a crippling parasitic disease caused by infection with &lt;em&gt;D. medinensis&lt;/em&gt;,
 a long, thread-like worm. It is usually transmitted when people drink 
stagnant water contaminated with parasite-infected water fleas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the 1980s, dracunculiasis was endemic in 20 countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finding
 and containing the last remaining cases, particularly in settings where
 there are security concerns and displaced populations, are the most 
difficult stages of the eradication process.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-------------------------------&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;The six cases are macroscopically consistent with guinea worm disease and are pending laboratory confirmation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;Containment centres have been set up in chosen locations in 
endemic regions of countries reporting active transmission of 
dracunculiasis. The centres are equipped to provide treatment and 
support to infected people to prevent them from contaminating drinking 
water sources.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;Temephos is a cyclopicide. It is used to kill water fleas (cyclops) that carry the infective guinea-worm larvae.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="false">urn:uuid:c851b234-ddb8-449c-bf1f-35e458cf9ebd</guid><link>https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/27-04-2020-who-timeline---covid-19</link><a10:author><a10:name> </a10:name></a10:author><title>WHO Timeline - COVID-19</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last updated 27 April&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;31 Dec 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wuhan Municipal Health Commission, China, reported &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/csr/don/05-january-2020-pneumonia-of-unkown-cause-china/en/"&gt;a cluster of cases of&lt;span style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;pneumonia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in
 Wuhan, Hubei Province. A novel coronavirus was eventually identified.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO had set up the IMST (Incident Management Support Team) across the three levels of the organization: headquarters, regional
    headquarters and country level, putting the organization on an emergency footing for dealing with the outbreak.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 &amp;nbsp;January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WHO/status/1213523866703814656?s=20"&gt;reported on social media&lt;/a&gt; that there was a cluster of pneumonia cases &amp;ndash; with no deaths &amp;ndash; in Wuhan, Hubei province.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO published our &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/csr/don/05-january-2020-pneumonia-of-unkown-cause-china/en/"&gt;first Disease Outbreak News&lt;/a&gt; on the new virus. This is a flagship technical publication to the scientific and public health community&amp;nbsp;as well as global media. It contained a risk assessment and advice, and reported
    on what China had told the organization about the status of patients and the public health response on the cluster of pneumonia cases in Wuhan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10 January 2020&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO issued a comprehensive package of technical guidance online with advice to all countries on how to detect, test and manage potential cases, based on what was known about the virus at the time.&amp;nbsp;This
    guidance was shared with WHO's regional emergency directors to share with WHO representatives in countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on experience with SARS and MERS and known modes of transmission of respiratory viruses, infection and prevention control guidance were published to protect health workers recommending droplet and contact precautions when caring for patients, and
    airborne precautions for aerosol generating procedures conducted by health workers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;China publicly&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/csr/don/12-january-2020-novel-coronavirus-china/en/"&gt;shared&lt;/a&gt; the genetic sequence of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong style="background-color:transparent;text-align:inherit;text-transform:inherit;white-space:inherit;word-spacing:normal;caret-color:auto;"&gt;13 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Officials confirm a case of &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/13-01-2020-who-statement-on-novel-coronavirus-in-thailand"&gt;COVID-19 in Thailand&lt;/a&gt;,
 the first recorded case outside of China. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO's technical lead for the response noted in a press briefing there may have been limited human-to-human transmission of the coronavirus (in the 41 confirmed cases), mainly through family members, and that there was a risk of a possible wider outbreak. The lead also said that human-to-human transmission would not be surprising given our experience with SARS, MERS and other respiratory pathogens. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20-21 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO experts from its China and Western Pacific regional offices conducted a brief field visit to Wuhan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;22 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;WHO mission to China&amp;nbsp;issued a &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/china/news/detail/22-01-2020-field-visit-wuhan-china-jan-2020"&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; saying that there was evidence of human-to-human transmission in Wuhan
    but more investigation was needed to understand the full extent of transmission.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;22- 23 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The WHO Director- General &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/23-01-2020-statement-on-the-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-outbreak-of-novel-coronavirus-(2019-ncov)"&gt;convened&lt;/a&gt; an Emergency Committee (EC) under the International Health Regulations (IHR 2005) to assess whether the outbreak constituted a public health
    emergency of international concern. The independent members from around the world could not reach a consensus based on the evidence available at the time. They asked to be reconvened within 10 days after receiving more information.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;28 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A senior WHO delegation led by the Director-General &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-01-2020-who-china-leaders-discuss-next-steps-in-battle-against-coronavirus-outbreak"&gt;travelled to Beijing to meet China&amp;rsquo;s leadership&lt;/a&gt;,
 learn more about China&amp;rsquo;s response, and to offer any technical assistance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While in Beijing, Dr. Tedros agreed with Chinese government leaders that an international team of leading scientists would travel to China on a mission to better understand the context, the overall response, and exchange information and experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30 January 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The WHO Director-General reconvened the &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/30-01-2020-statement-on-the-second-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-outbreak-of-novel-coronavirus-(2019-ncov)"&gt;Emergency Committee (EC)&lt;/a&gt;. This was earlier than the 10-day period and only two days after the first reports of limited human-to-human transmission were reported outside China. This time, the EC reached consensus and advised the Director-General that the outbreak constituted a Public Health Emergency of International Concern (PHEIC). The Director-General accepted the recommendation and declared the novel coronavirus outbreak (2019-nCoV) a PHEIC.&amp;nbsp;This is the 6th time WHO has declared a PHEIC since the International Health Regulations (IHR) came into force in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/situation-reports/20200130-sitrep-10-ncov.pdf?sfvrsn=d0b2e480_2"&gt;situation report&lt;/a&gt; for 30 January reported 7818 total confirmed cases worldwide, with the majority of these in China, and&amp;nbsp;82 cases reported in 18 countries outside China. WHO gave a risk assessment of very high for China, and high at the global level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 February 2020&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO releases the international community's&amp;nbsp;&lt;a title="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/strategic-preparedness-and-response-plan-for-the-new-coronavirus" href="https://www.who.int/publications-detail/strategic-preparedness-and-response-plan-for-the-new-coronavirus"&gt;Strategic Preparedness and Response Plan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to help protect states with weaker health systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11-12 February 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO convened a &lt;a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/12-02-2020-world-experts-and-funders-set-priorities-for-covid-19-research"&gt;Research and Innovation Forum&lt;/a&gt; on COVID-19, attended by more than 400 experts and funders from around the world, which included presentations by&amp;nbsp;George Gao, Director General of China CDC, and Zunyou Wu, China CDC's chief epidemiologist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16-24 February 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The WHO-China Joint mission, which included experts&amp;nbsp;from Canada, Germany, Japan, Nigeria, Republic of Korea, Russia, Singapore and the US (CDC, NIH)&amp;nbsp;spent time in Beijing and also travelled to
    Wuhan and two other cities. They spoke with health officials, scientists and health workers in health facilities (maintaining physical distancing). The report of the joint mission can be found here:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-china-joint-mission-on-covid-19-final-report.pdf?sfvrsn=fce87f4e_2"&gt;https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-china-joint-mission-on-covid-19-final-report.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11 March 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deeply concerned both by the alarming levels of spread and severity, and by the alarming levels of inaction, WHO&amp;nbsp;made the assessment that COVID-19 can be characterized as a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13 March 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/donate" href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/donate"&gt;COVID-19 Solidarity Response Fund&lt;/a&gt; launched to receive donations from private individuals, corporations and institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18 March 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHO and partners launch the &lt;a title="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/global-research-on-novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov/solidarity-clinical-trial-for-covid-19-treatments" href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/global-research-on-novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov/solidarity-clinical-trial-for-covid-19-treatments"&gt;Solidarity Trial&lt;/a&gt;, an international clinical trial that aims to generate robust data from around the world to find the most effective treatments for COVID-19.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 16:21:40 Z</pubDate></item></channel></rss>